<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The history of the state of the present war in Hungary, Austria, Croatia, Moravia, and Silesia between Leopold Emperour of Germany, and Mahamet the fourth Sultan of the Turks, in conjunction with Count Teckely and the Hungarian rebels. Giving an exact account of all the remarkable transactions from the beginning of the war, as sieges, battles, cessations, truces, treaties, denunciation of war, skirmishes, and other hostilities, to this time; but more particularly of the siege of Vienna, and the last great battle, &amp;c. To which is added, a relation of the miseries the Christian captives undergo in Turky. All faithfully related according to the best and most authentick advice. By J. S. gent.</title>
            <author>J. S. (John Shirley), fl. 1680-1702.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1683</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 177 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 83 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A62163</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S67</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R219066</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99830599</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99830599</idno>
            <idno type="VID">35052</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A62163)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 35052)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2077:06)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The history of the state of the present war in Hungary, Austria, Croatia, Moravia, and Silesia between Leopold Emperour of Germany, and Mahamet the fourth Sultan of the Turks, in conjunction with Count Teckely and the Hungarian rebels. Giving an exact account of all the remarkable transactions from the beginning of the war, as sieges, battles, cessations, truces, treaties, denunciation of war, skirmishes, and other hostilities, to this time; but more particularly of the siege of Vienna, and the last great battle, &amp;c. To which is added, a relation of the miseries the Christian captives undergo in Turky. All faithfully related according to the best and most authentick advice. By J. S. gent.</title>
                  <author>J. S. (John Shirley), fl. 1680-1702.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10], 147, [1] p., [1] leaf of plates : ill.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for William Whitwood, next to the George Inn in Little-Britain,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1683.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>J. S. gent. = John Shirley.</note>
                  <note>Includes a final advertisement page.</note>
                  <note>Pages faded, affecting text.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Turkey --  History --  Mehmed IV, 1648-1687 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:35052:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:35052:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE HISTORY OF THE STATE OF THE <hi>Preſent War</hi> IN <hi>Hungary, Auſtria, Croatia, Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ravia,</hi> and <hi>Sileſia:</hi> Between <hi>Leopold</hi> Emperour of <hi>Germa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny,</hi> and <hi>Mahumet</hi> the Fourth, Sultan of the <hi>Turks,</hi> in conjunction with Count <hi>Teckely</hi> and the <hi>Hungarian</hi> Rebels. Giving an exact ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of all the remarkable tranſactions from the beginning of the War, As Sieges, Battles, Ceſſations, Truces, Treaties, Denunciation of War, Skirmiſhes, and other Hoſtilities, to this Time; but more particularly of the Siege of <hi>Vienna,</hi> and the laſt great Battle, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> To which is added, A Relation of the miſeries the Chriſtian Captives undergo in <hi>Turky.</hi> All faithfully related according to the beſt and moſt authentick advice.</p>
            <p>By <hi>J. S.</hi> Gent.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>William Whitwood,</hi> next to the <hi>George Inn</hi> in <hi>Little-Britain.</hi> 1683.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="frontispiece">
            <pb facs="tcp:35052:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:35052:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:35052:3"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figure>
                     <head>The Grand Seignor</head>
                  </figure>
                  <figure>
                     <head>Count Teckley</head>
                  </figure>
                  <figure>
                     <head>The Emporour of Germany</head>
                  </figure>
                  <figure>
                     <head>The Duke of Lorraine</head>
                  </figure>
                  <figure>
                     <head>The Viſier Baſſa</head>
                  </figure>
                  <head>
                     <l>Behold the Wounded Empire, Bleeding Lyes.</l>
                     <l>By Rebells Rage and Turkiſh Cruelties</l>
                     <l>(But what's the cauſe) it springs from Chriſtian was</l>
                     <l>The Turkes Still Triumphs when the Chriſtians jar.</l>
                  </head>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:35052:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:35052:4"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:35052:4"/>
            <head>THE EPISTLE TO THE READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Shall here preſent you with a mournful Account of the afflicted State of <hi>Hungaria, Auſtria,</hi> and other Chriſtian Countries, now groaning under the Oppreſſion of the Turkiſh Sword, for at this time (as it has been always obſerved, and indeed the only Policy by which the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Empire has arrived to its Extent and Greatneſs) the preſent Emperour <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>homet Han,</hi> the Fourteenth Monarch of the <hi>Turks,</hi> moved thereto for vain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glory,
<pb facs="tcp:35052:5"/>and to get him a Name equal to that of his Anceſtors; an Ambition much ſought by the Turkiſh Monarchs) taking the advantage of the Chriſtians Diviſions amongſt themſelves, (a thing alwayes fatal to <hi>Chriſtendom,</hi> and a furtherance to the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Affairs, as giving their Arms a more eaſie pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs, which Diviſion the <hi>Turks</hi> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute to proceed from the Effects of their Prayers to their Impoſtor <hi>Mahomet,</hi> whom they ſtile their Interceſſor) has for ſome years paſt wounded deep the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire, now grown weak by the many ſtreams of Blood drawn by Civil Broils, and bandying againſt its powerful Chriſtian Neighbours; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch that at this day thoſe barbarous Infidels triumph and revel, not only in the Cities of <hi>Hungary</hi> and <hi>Crotia,</hi> but even in the chief Cities of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> the only Bulwark of the Empire; to defend which, in former times, ſome Millions of Lives have been loſt. And
<pb facs="tcp:35052:5"/>thus far have they advanced without any colour or warrant for their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings, more than a pretence of Pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, to aſſist the rebellious <hi>Hungars,</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Leading of their obſtinate and turbulent General, <hi>Count Tecke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> a man whom no Favours, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſions, or Indulgences of his Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and Natural Prince can prevail upon, or work to a Submiſsion or Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliation; but deſirous of that pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stilent Bain, Greatneſs, rather than go without it, he, with an unrelenting heart, dares wade to it through the Bowels of his bleeding Countrey, and help the Infidels in their Cruelty; though moſt are of opinion, and not without good grounds, that the <hi>Turk,</hi> having obtained his Ends, and glut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted himſelf with the Treaſon, the Traytor will be of no farther uſe, and if ſuffered to live, it will be paſt doubt in Confinement: for 'tis a true Max<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>im in Potentates, They love the <hi>Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:35052:6"/>but the <hi>Traytor</hi> they hate. And now, ſince upon the great Events of this War the Eyes of all men are fix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, (for indeed it concerns the whole Chriſtian World) I have thought fit, for the better Information and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction of my Countrey-men, to give an impartial account of the Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actions and Events of the diſaſtrous War, whoſe End is yet uncertain; for if the Infidels, now powerful in the Field, and ſtrongly ingarriſoned in many commanding Cities, have not a stop put to their Incroachment by the ſpeedy uniting and combination of the Christian Princes, or from the imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate hand of Heaven, the <hi>German</hi> Empire will run a hazard to be great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſhattered and diſinembred, if not totally lost, which Heaven prevent. And certainly, the miſerable ſlaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters and captivities already made, ought to incline the most ambitious Prince, if not for his Neighbour's
<pb facs="tcp:35052:6"/>ſake, yet for his own, and his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treys Preſervation, and by timely op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing the Torrent, damm up that Stream, that with impetuous Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence ſeeks to overflow all before it, and be a warning to other Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Nations, of what they muſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect, if the Infidels are permitted to proceed, and uncontrouled, in a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, wade through Blood and Slaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, deſtroying with Fire and Sword all pleaſant Places as they paſs, glory<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in nothing more than to trample under foot, and tread upon the Necks of the diſtreſſed Chriſtians; whom, like a Flock of Sheep, they drive be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them like Wretches deſtined for ſlaughter, or perpetual Bondage, at the pleaſure of the Tyrant. But to come nearer to my purpoſe;</p>
            <p>Reader, I ſhall in this Tract pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent you with the <hi>Series</hi> of the War, as it has been tranſacted, either in
<pb facs="tcp:35052:7"/>Battels, Skirmiſhes, burning of Towns and Villages, Sieges, Ravages, taking of Priſoners, Contributions, and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actions, the numbers of the ſlain, as they occur, and divers other Matters, but more eſpecially the Siege of the great City of <hi>Vienna,</hi> ſo long the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perial Seat of the <hi>German</hi> Empire, and chief City of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> relating ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actly, as it has come to my hand, the divers paſſages happening during the ſaid Siege.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, I ſhall preſent you with a brief <hi>Compendium</hi> of Turkiſh Cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties both in Peace and War, to ſuch Chriſtians as they carry into miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Bondage; and many other things which I here for brevities ſake omit to mention; but ſhall at large in the following Hiſtory expoſe to view. And ſo with my hearty Prayers to Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God to put a ſtop to the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs of this Tyrant, by ſending a
<pb facs="tcp:35052:7"/>Spirit of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity and Concord amongſt the Chriſtian Princes, that all as one man, they may unite their Forces for the preſervation of what yet remains free in <hi>Chriſtendom.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Reader, I remain Yours to ſerve You,</hi> J. S.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:35052:8"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head>The Cittie of Vienna Beſeiged by the turkes with the forme of the battle between the Chriſtian And turkes</head>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:35052:8"/>
            <head>THE STATE OF THE <hi>Preſent War</hi> Between the <hi>Turks</hi> and <hi>Imperials</hi> IN <hi>H<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>NGARIA, A<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>STRIA,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <p>THE <hi>Grand Seignior,</hi> having a long time ſought for an opportunity to incroach upon <hi>Chriſtendom,</hi> he, in order to effect the ſame, by ſundry means tempted the <hi>Hungarian</hi> Male-contents, prone enough of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to take up Arms againſt their Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Sovereign, under the ſpecious preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Liberty of Conſcience, free Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe in Religion, and caſting off the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perial
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:35052:9"/>Juriſdiction, in renouncing Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to the Emperour. And to carry on that Deſign, allured <hi>Teckely,</hi> their Ring-leader, with many ſpecious Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, to riſe in Rebellion; who, ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious of Preferment and Advancement to the Title of Prince of <hi>Tranſylvania,</hi> or King of <hi>Hungaria,</hi> more than any motive to promote, preſerve, or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagate the Reformed Religion, drawing after him a great number of his Follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, ſeized upon many Villages, and by Surprize, took ſome Fortreſſes in <hi>Crotia,</hi> and the Borders of <hi>Hungary</hi> on that ſide, which drew a great number of the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>affected to take part with him: So that he came formidable e're the News of the Rebellion had reached the Emperours Ears, being all along aſſiſted under-hand by the Turks with Money and Muniti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, notwithſtanding there was peace be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the two Empires. But certain it is that, then acient ſaying is moſt apparent, <hi>viz.</hi> That the <hi>Turks</hi> never kept any League longer than it tends to their Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage.</p>
            <p>To heighten the Deſign, whilſt the <hi>Turks</hi> on the one part were caſting in
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:35052:9"/>Thoughts the future War, the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Princes were as earneſtly involved in a War amongſt themſelves, rather ſeek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to deſtroy each other then mindful of the common Enemy, who all the while was undermining the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire; till at length his Imperial Majeſty per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving the drift of the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Sultan, uſed his Diligence to fruſtrate his Deſign, firſt by immediately diſpatching Orders to his Ambaſſador at the Port to complain of the Baſſa's of <hi>Buda</hi> and <hi>Effen,</hi> for aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Rebel-Subjects, and to deſire that a right Underſtanding might be conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued between the two Empires, and the Peace inviolably obſerved; and at the ſame time publiſhed divers Edicts or De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clarations, expreſſing his Willingneſs to pardon the Rebeis if they would return to their former Obedience; as likewiſe, how ready he was to ſatisfie his Subjects of that his Hereditary Country of <hi>Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garia</hi> in all their reaſonable Demands, and would alow them a competent num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Churches, wherein they ſhould have the free exerciſe of their Religion, with ſuch Privileges as his Roman Catholick Subjects of that Kingdon injoyed. In
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:35052:10"/>anſwer to the firſt he received many fair Promiſes, and from the Grand <hi>Viſier,</hi> an aſſurance of an amicable Correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, right Underſtanding, and an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>violable League between the two Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pires; with a Promiſe, that no farther Aſſiſtance ſhould be given to the <hi>Hunga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian</hi> Rebels; but, that if upon inquiry the <hi>Baſſas, Sanzacks,</hi> or Governours of any Garriſon in <hi>Hungaria,</hi> or on the Frontires, ſhould underſtand or openly aſſiſt the Rebels, he or they ſhould incur the Grand Seigniors high Diſpleaſure, and conſequently, be puniſhed with Death; though at the ſame time the <hi>Baſſa</hi> of <hi>Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da</hi> had private orders from the Port to countenance the Rebels, and keep them in Heart till matters were Ripe for the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Sword to put in.</p>
            <p>The effects of the ſecond device, or intention of the Emperour to counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine the <hi>Turk,</hi> ſucceeded no better, or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed rather worſe; for although ſome ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt Perſons, and many of the <hi>Hungarian</hi> Gentry, who had been unadviſedly drawn into the Rebellion, did embrace the Imperial Grace and Favour, laying down their Arms, and retiring to their
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:35052:10"/>reſpective Habitations, yet <hi>Teckely</hi> and his followers, who had abſolutely, as moſt imagine, determined to have no Peace (had the Emperour granted more than themſelves demanded) held out to oppoſe, whom divers Troops were ſent under the command of Count <hi>Caprara,</hi> and other Captains, to repreſs them, and another Edict publiſhed, to oblige them to come in, promiſing them a Pala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine of their own Nation; and that in caſe of Offices and Places of Truſt, no di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction ſhould be made between his Subjects of either Religion.</p>
            <p>Upon theſe Propoſals, the <hi>Turks</hi> fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Male contents might come to the Emperours Propoſitions, and that by their diſſerting their Leaders, and laying down their Arms, might hinder their Deſigns, they reſolved to be fiſhing whilſt the Water was troubled; and thereupon began to take off the vizard and appear more openly to countenance the Rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the great <hi>Baſſa</hi> ſending Supplies of Men and Money to the Rebels frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: and when a ſecond complaint was made at the Port, by the Count <hi>Capra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra,</hi> the Imperial Ambaſſador there reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:35052:11"/>he found the face of Things chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, and War ſilently threatned. The Grand Seignior having throughout his <hi>Aſian</hi> and <hi>African</hi> Territories cauſed Men to be raiſed, and ſummoned ſuch as held Land of him to ſerve in the War, to repair with Horſe and Arms to the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Randezvous near <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out the Horſe taile, thereby ſignify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing himſelf intended to take the Field.</p>
            <p>The Emperour, adviſed of theſe Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parations, drew ſeveral Detachments out of his Army, incamped near the <hi>Rhine</hi> to have an Eye upon the <hi>French,</hi> who had poſſeſſed themſelves of <hi>Strasburg,</hi> an Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perial free City: the Forces were ſent un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the leading of the Count <hi>Staremberg</hi> to joyn Count <hi>Caprara;</hi> who with a Body of 7000 had ſecured the Paſſes of the <hi>Waag,</hi> and a Commiſſion directed to the Pala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine to raiſe the Ban, and the Arrear Ban of the Kingdom, whilſt the electoral Princes met at <hi>Oldenburg,</hi> to conſult what meaſures were to be taken in order to the preſervation of <hi>Hungaria,</hi> and quieting the Rebellion, being earneſtly preſſed thereto by his Imperial Majeſty.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:35052:11"/>
            <p>Things being at this paſs, divers Skir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſhes paſſed between Parties in <hi>Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garia,</hi> with various Succeſs, when as to ſtrengthen himſelf, and the better to In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratiate with the <hi>Hungarians,</hi> he having married the Princeſs <hi>Ragozki,</hi> and recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved a new ſupply from the <hi>Baſſa</hi> or <hi>Offen,</hi> which <hi>Baſſa</hi> with 15000 <hi>Turks</hi> had like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe took the Field; he drew down before <hi>Chaſchaw,</hi> and, after ſix or ſeven days battering it, had it ſurrendred; the Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon being permitted to depart with Bag and Bagage; heightned with this Succeſs, he brayed the Imperial General, being by his own Faction ſaluted King of <hi>Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gary,</hi> and to ſecure his Wives Patrimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, put a ſtrong Garriſon into <hi>Mongaſa,</hi> ſummoning the <hi>Hungarian</hi> Nobility and Gentry to attend him in Arms at a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Randeſvouz near <hi>Levents;</hi> but, they weighing their Duty &amp; Allegiance to their Sovereign, few of them came; whereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Parties were ſent out to burn and plun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Houſes of divers of them, one of which Parties Count <hi>Straſoldo</hi> meeting with, utterly defeated them, killing ſix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty on the Place and taking 100 Priſoners.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:35052:12"/>
            <p>During theſe Tranſactions, the <hi>Vizier Baſſa</hi> having drawn 20000 Horſe and Foot into the Field, beſieged <hi>Zathmar;</hi> and Count <hi>Tekely</hi> ſat down before <hi>Eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries,</hi> which he upon the firſt Summons had ſurrendered into his Hands; and after that beſieged <hi>Lewents:</hi> the Rumour of which did not a little alarm the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perialiſts, when, the better to ſtay the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs of the Enemy, and to prevent the <hi>Tranſylvanian</hi> Princes joyning with <hi>Tec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kely,</hi> who for that purpoſe had muſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed 11000 Horſe and Foot, the greateſt part of them <hi>Tartars,</hi> who had a little be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore paſſed the <hi>Neiſter.</hi> The Imperial Troops in <hi>Moravia, Sileſia,</hi> and <hi>Behemia,</hi> together with the Troops in the other Hereditary Countries of the Empire, mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched to <hi>Wang</hi> to reinforce the Imperial Camp, upon which <hi>Teckely,</hi> doubting the Succeſs of their Arms, ſent his Depu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties to Count <hi>Caprara,</hi> to deſire that he might ſend to the Emperour to treat about a Truce, and that in order thereto he might have Paſports of ſafe Conduct allowed him whom he ſhould imploy in that Affair, the which, after ſome diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty, he obtained, and a Ceſſation for ſix
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:35052:12"/>weeks was concluded; but, <hi>Teckely</hi> find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Power of the <hi>Turks</hi> increaſe, and having 1000 <hi>Janizaries</hi> allow'd him for the Guard of his Perſon, though at the ſame time there was an evil Underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing between him and the Prince of <hi>Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſylvania,</hi> the latter being jealous that the former would be by the Grand Seignior inveſted in his Principality. He, I ſay, notwithſtanding, adventured to break the Truce e're it was half expir'd, by commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting divers Hoſtilities, burning and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroying many Villages; Then fetching a Compaſs about, he covered with his Army <hi>Villecke,</hi> whilſt the <hi>Baſſa</hi> of <hi>Buda</hi> beſieged it with 25000 <hi>Turks</hi> and <hi>Tartars,</hi> which City made a long and brave Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance, but in the end, perceiving no releif at hand, and moſt of their Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion and Ammunition ſpent, they capi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tulated with the beſieged; the Souldiers and Townſmen doing it without the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of the Governour, and on the ſix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth of September 1682 ſurrendred it into the hands of the <hi>Baſſa,</hi> and all but the Governour ſuffered to March out with Bag and Bagage, the Governour by reaſon of his not conſenting to ſign the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:35052:13"/>Capitulation he was made a Priſoner of War.</p>
            <p>To this Town <hi>Teckely</hi> layed claim, alledging that the Grand Seignior had promiſed that ſuch Places as were taken in <hi>Hungary</hi> during the War, ſhould be furniſhed with <hi>Hungarian</hi> Gariſons, which occaſioned a ſharp Conteſt between them; when, after divers conſiderations and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bates, wherein they appeared to be jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous of each other, it was concluded, to end the debate, that the Place ſhould be demoliſhed, which with fire and blowing up was accordingly done, and all the Walls levelled with the Ground; at what time <hi>Lewents,</hi> a Place not tenable, being much conſternated upon the near<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of ſo formidable an Army, was both by its Inhabitants and the Imperial Gari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon abandoned, and thereupon poſſeſſed by the Enemy; and Count <hi>Caprara</hi> finding himſelf far inferiour in ſtrength and number, raiſed his Camp near <hi>Atſol,</hi> and retired towards St. <hi>Croix,</hi> to joyn the <hi>Hungarian</hi> Palatine, who had drawn a conſiderable Body into the Field, and incamped near <hi>Torney.</hi> About which time advice came from the Count <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prara,</hi>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:35052:13"/>to inform his Imperial Majeſty, that in conſideration <hi>Warradine</hi> and <hi>Rabb</hi> two of the ſtrongeſt Pieces in <hi>Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gary</hi> might be ſurrendered, the Grand Seignior would renew the League for the ſpace of twenty Years, but this being look'd upon only as an Artifice to gain time, and that if the <hi>Turks</hi> poſſeſſed thoſe important Places all the reſt would be ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily gotten, there was nothing farther ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotiated as to that affair.</p>
            <p>Winter growing on, the <hi>Turks</hi> and <hi>Hungarian</hi> Rebels having ſeized themſelvs of the Fortreſſes of <hi>Atſol, Neuſol, Schmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitz</hi> and <hi>Cremnitz,</hi> by a Command from the <hi>Vizier</hi> of <hi>Buda,</hi> abandoned them, as either not thinking them tenable, or that the charge in maintaining them would be greater then the advantage; yet e're they left them, they blew up the Works, broke down the Walls, and diſmant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led moſt of the Houſes, carrying away divers Perſons Priſoners to <hi>Buda, Grand Novagrade</hi> and other Garriſons adjacent.</p>
            <p>This being in general the State of Affairs, and of this War, <hi>Anno</hi> 1680, 1681 and 1682, I ſhall for the time en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing take a more exact Survey of par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Tranſactions.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:35052:14"/>
            <p>The Emperour, finding by this time that there was no Faith amongſt the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidels, and little or none to be given to the fair pretences of his Rebels, who ſtill pretended they took up Arms for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving and maintaining their Religion and Liberties, which the <hi>Turk<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſh Sultan</hi> aſſured them by his <hi>Baſſas,</hi> ſhould be both enjoy'd, if his and their Arms prevailed, and finding his own Forces too weak to oppoſe ſo great a Torrent as was flowing from all Parts of the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Empire, againſt the Spring, he negotiated by his Miniſters an offenſive and defenſive League with the King of <hi>Poland;</hi> which upon the firſt motion, found great oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition by the perverſe Party, aſſembled in the Diet, who are ever deſirous to keep peace with the <hi>Turks,</hi> by reaſon their Hereditary Eſtates lye on the Fron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiers, and are ſubject to be ſpoyl'd by the <hi>Turks</hi> Garriſons: but upon the arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>val of Count <hi>Walſtain,</hi> his Imperial Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties Ambaſſador in that great Affair; they ſeemed more pliable, and gave or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der for the Ambaſſador's reception in the moſt ſplendid manner, paſſing a Decree that 20000 Men ſhould be inſtantly raiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:35052:14"/>for the defence of the Kingdom; and that although the Diet ſhould break up abruptly by reaſon of the Proteſtation of any of the Deputies, (which often happens, for if any of them proteſt againſt the proceedings, the Diet is diſſolved, unleſs his Aſſent can within 24 hours be procur'd,) the ſaid Decree ſhould ſtand good.</p>
            <p>The Negotiation in the <hi>Poliſh</hi> Court going on ſuccesfully, Count <hi>Teckely</hi> fell to his former Artifices, feigning himſelf deſirous of nothing more than to come to a Peace with the Emperour, ſignifying by his Secretary to the Imperial Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, that it had for ſome time paſt been his chiefeſt care and buſineſs to prolong the Truce, and perſwade the <hi>Turks</hi> to a Compliance, and that in order thereto, he had written to the Grand Signior, inſomuch that he hoped an Honourable Peace toight be on the part of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour obtain'd.</p>
            <p>Theſe overtures made many hope that himſelf would at leaſt come in and accept the offered Grace, Pardon, and Favour of his Imperial Majeſty, but ſuch hopes ſoon after vaniſhed, for <hi>Teckely</hi> perceiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:35052:15"/>that a League would be concluded between the Emperour and King of <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> having daily notice of the Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces towards it from ſuch of his Faction as reſided at the <hi>Polonian</hi> Court, he cauſed the Eſtates of <hi>Hungary,</hi> as many as were under the Juriſdiction of his Arms, to aſſemble at <hi>Caſchaw,</hi> where they, to the number of ſix, met; and the end for which they were aſſembled openly decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, which was in theſe or the like Words delivered by the Adjutant or Speaker; <hi>viz.</hi> Foraſmuch as the ſaid Count had, to the hazard of his Life and Fortune, adventured in all Dangers to maintain the War for the Protection and Preſervation of their Religion and Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties, and was ready at all times to ſpend his Life on that occaſion, it there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore behoved them in Gratitude to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider his Services paſt, and have in mind the proſpect of what he might farther ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage them in, and that it was no time now to look back, ſeeing they had all ſo highly incurred the Emperour's Diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure; or if they ſhould, then they would break their Words with the <hi>Grand Seig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nior,</hi> whoſe powerful Army would ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:35052:15"/>be upon them, and that without a Head they could not ſubſiſt without Faction and Diviſion amongſt themſelves; therefore if they made choice of one, they could not better do than to chuſe the Count, a Man, as he ſaid, not only of approved Valour and Conduct, but a Man approved of by the <hi>Grand Seignior,</hi> and beloved by the neighbouring Baſſa's; inſomuch that they need not fear the Emperour's Indignation, for that they ſhould always have a power at hand able to repell his Forces; and as for their Liberties, Religion, and an eaſie Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute, they might aſſure themſelves; the Grand Seignior, having ſolemnly vow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed not to alter any thing in the former two, nor ſuppreſs or be exacting in the latter, deſigning no more than a bare Acknowledgment of his Sovereignty for the two firſt Years.</p>
            <p>This Oration ended, many were ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prized, as not expecting any ſuch matter, though divers of his Faction highly appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved it; ſaying he ought and ſhould be their Prince, and by Threats and Cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors carried it, uſing divers Ceremonies to confirm him therein, and ſoon after,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:35052:16"/>he was ſaluted as ſuch by the <hi>Baſſa's,</hi> who ſent to congratulate him: when proud of his unjuſt Title, he ſent out Parties into divers part of the Kingdom to ſpoil and plunder ſuch as were not conſenting to his Promotion, or refuſ'd to acknowledg him in that capacity.</p>
            <p>By this time the Emperour had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded an Offenſive and Defenſive League with his Electoral Highneſs of <hi>Bavaria,</hi> by which the latter was to raiſe 10000 Men for the Service of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, the Charges after they are raiſed to be defrayed by the Emperour; and his Electoral Highneſs at his own Charge to maintain 3000 more in the Emperour's Service againſt the <hi>Turk</hi> in <hi>Hungary.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whilſt <hi>Teckely</hi> and the <hi>Turks</hi> domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neer'd in <hi>Hungary,</hi> an Expreſs arrived at <hi>Vienna,</hi> ſent by the Count <hi>Caprara,</hi> the Emperours Ambaſſador, then reſiding at <hi>Adrianople,</hi> to aquaint his Majeſty that he had held a Conference with the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ga</hi> of the <hi>Janizaries,</hi> the ſaid <hi>Aga</hi> had demanded of him, whether the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour his Maſter did accept of the Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſals, that ſome time ſince had been made by the Grand Seignior, <hi>viz.</hi> That his Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perial
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:35052:16"/>Majeſty ſhould yield to the <hi>Grand Seignior</hi> the Fortreſſes of <hi>Commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra</hi> and <hi>Rabb,</hi> with the Iſlands of <hi>Schuts, Rabaw,</hi> and <hi>Setin,</hi> and that in conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion thereof, the <hi>Grand Seignior</hi> would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>new the Peace with his Imperial Majeſty, and that He the ſaid Count <hi>Caprara</hi> had returned for anſwer, that he had not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived any Inſtructions from his Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial Majeſty relating to theſe Propoſals, much leſs, Orders to agree to them. To which the proud <hi>Aga</hi> replied, That ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing theſe things could not be obtained by Treaty, nor they grant the <hi>Grand Seignior</hi>'s Demands, he would proceed to obtain them by Fire and Sword; and thereupon ordering the Count to return to his Lodging, he went directly to the <hi>Grand Vizier,</hi> and inform'd him what an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer he had received to his Propoſals, ſaying, that there were no hopes of ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining their deſires by Treaty. This ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice being tranſmitted by the <hi>Vizier</hi> to the <hi>Grand Seignior,</hi> he in a great rage commanded the ſame afternoon the Horſe tail to be hung out upon a Pole, which is an infallible token that the <hi>Grand Seig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nior</hi> or the <hi>Grand Vizier</hi> intend to take the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:35052:17"/>Field, and, as it were, a tacit denuncia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of War, being a <hi>memorandum</hi> of the <hi>Turks</hi> rudeneſs in their original. He like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe diſpatched away Orders to the <hi>Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarian Kam,</hi> commanding him thereby to draw together his diſperſed Forces, and with all the celerity imaginable march towards <hi>Hungaria,</hi> there to meet him up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his arrival. The like Orders he cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to be diſpatched to the <hi>Vavods,</hi> or Princes of <hi>Valachia, Moldavia,</hi> and <hi>Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſylvania,</hi> enjoyning alſo Count <hi>Teckely</hi> to be ready early in the Spring, with the greateſt Power he could draw together; appointing the <hi>Aga</hi> of the <hi>Janizaries</hi> to march with the Avaunt guard of the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, on the 28th of <hi>March,</hi> himſelf in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending with the Groſs of his Army, by this time aſſembled out of <hi>Aſia, Anatolia, Egypt</hi> the greater and leſſer, out of <hi>Pelo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponneſus, Boſna, Bulgaria, Servia, Epirus,</hi> and other Countries under his ſubjecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, to the number of 180000 Horſe and Foot; and for his reception gave order for erecting a ſtately Houſe at <hi>Belgrade.</hi> And the better to expoſe himſelf in his proper Colours, and appear a Turk, he cauſed this denuntiation of War, boaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:35052:17"/>and Biaſphemous: A Copy of which I ſhall give you <hi>verbatim,</hi> as 'tis credibly related to be faithfully tranſlated out of <hi>High Dutch,</hi> and intitled,
<q>A Declaration, or Denunciation of WAR;</q>
            </p>
            <p>Which <hi>Sultan Mahomet</hi> the 4th; pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Emperour of the <hi>Turks,</hi> ſent to the Emperour of <hi>Germany,</hi> dated <hi>March</hi> 25. 1683. from <hi>Adrianople,</hi> juſt as the Baron <hi>Saphonara,</hi> his Imperial Majeſtie's Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, had his laſt Audience of the Prince <hi>Vizier,</hi> wherein the ſaid Miniſter could not comply with the unreaſonable De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands of the <hi>Turk;</hi> which cauſed the <hi>Grand Seignior</hi> to tranſmit the ſame to his <hi>Imperial Majeſty.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>The Denunciation, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>MAhomer</hi> the 4<hi rend="sup">th.</hi> Son of Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours, and of the Famous and Renowned God, Emperour of the <hi>Turks,</hi> King of <hi>Greece, Macedonia, Molda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>via, Samaria,</hi> and <hi>Hegha,</hi> King of the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:35052:18"/>great and leſſer <hi>Egypt,</hi> King of all the Inhabitants of the Earth, and Prince of the Earthly Paradice, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged Prince, and Son of <hi>Maho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met,</hi> Preſerver of the Cities of <hi>Hunga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria,</hi> Poſſeſſor of the Sepulchre of your God, Lord of all the Emperours of the World, from the riſing of the Sun to the going down thereof, King of all Kings, Lord of the Tree of Life, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querour of the <hi>Melonian Hegeley</hi> and the City of <hi>Prolenix,</hi> great Perſecutor of the <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> and all wicked Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, Joy of the flouriſhing World, Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander and Guardian of your cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied God, Lord of the Multitude of Heathens:</p>
            <p>We command you to greet the Emperour <hi>Leopold,</hi> in caſe he deſire it, and you are a Friend to our Majeſty, whoſe Power we will extend very far: You have for ſome time paſt acted to our prejudice, and viola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Our Friendſhip, though We have not offended you by War or otherwiſe; You have taken Counſel and Advice with other Kings
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:35052:18"/>and Princes how to ſhake off your yoak, in which you have proceeded very indiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creetly, and thereby have expoſed your Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to fear and danger, who have nothing now to expect but Death, which you have brought upon your ſelves; for I declare I will make my ſelf your Maſter, and purſue you from Eaſt to Weſt, and extend my Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty to the End of the World. In the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedure of all which, you ſhall find my Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er exerted to your extreme Prejudice, and ſhall feel the dreadful Effects of my wrath. And ſince you have put your hopes and truſt in the strength of ſome Towns and Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, I have given command to overthrow them, and trample under my Horſes Feet all that is delightful in your Eyes, leaving you no room hereafter to make Friendſhip with me, nor ſuffer you to keep any fortified Place wherein to put your trust, for I have reſolved forthwith to destroy you and all your People, and to deſpoil you of the <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> Empire, after my Will and Pleaſure, leaving in the Empire a ſad remembrance of my dreadful Sword; that it may pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickly appear that I have eſtabliſhed my Religion therein, and purſued your cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied God, whoſe wrath I fear not, nor his
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:35052:19"/>coming to defend and deliver you out of my hands; but will condemn your Sacred Prieſts to the Plow, and ſuffer the Breaſts of your Wives and Matrons to be ſucked by Dogs and other Beaſts. You will do well to forſake your Religion, or I will give order to conſume you with Fire. This is enough to let you underſtand my Will, if you will be ſo wiſe as to know it.</p>
            <p>This vain-glorious and blaſphemous belching againſt Heaven and Earth, did not at all terrifie his Imperial Majeſty, as to his own particular, being a Prince of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daunted Courage, and unſhaken Reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, yet grieved, as indeed all Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans ought, and highly concerned to hear the Worlds Redeemer, in whoſe hands are all the corners of the Earth, who holds the Winds in the hollow of his Hands, and reſtrains the deep as with a Bridle, in whoſe Power is all the Breath of Life, and who can with a word diſſolve all things into <hi>Chaos,</hi> reviled and blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemed by this River Leviathan, this peice of duſt and aſhes, but man at moſt, and ſubject to all Infirmities; but when the Almighty deſigns to puniſh his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:35052:19"/>it has been frequently obſerved that he raiſes up ſuch like Inſtruments, yet when he has ſcourged them ſufficiently caſts the rod into the fire, as in this caſe may be expected, and is by Prophecies both ſacred and moral foretold.</p>
            <p>His Imperial Majeſty following the precedent of <hi>Hezekia</hi> King of <hi>Juda</hi> when <hi>Rabſheka</hi> in the like manner with blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemies upbraided him with the want of Power in the God whom he ſerved to deliver him out of the hands of his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter the King of <hi>Aſſyria,</hi> he firſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted his cauſe to God and relied upon him for protection, cauſing publick Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers and Faſting to be obſerved, and then communicated the matter to the Electo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Princes at <hi>Ratisbone,</hi> requiring them not to be wanting in their duty, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend the Empire; and above the reſt preſſed his Electoral Highneſs of <hi>Branden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burg,</hi> as the beſt able, to ſend a conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able force into the field, ſending to the Vice-roy of <hi>Crotia</hi> and <hi>Palatine</hi> of <hi>Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gary</hi> to draw together what forces they could; from whom he received an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, that the Eſtates and Gentry of ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Countrey would raiſe ſo great a
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:35052:20"/>Summ of money as ſhould maintain 10000 in his Imperial ſervice, with which the Emperor ſeemed highly plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed; and having notice that Count <hi>Tec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kely</hi> began to draw his Troops out of their Winter quarters, he diſpatched three new raiſed Regiments of foot and one of Horſe to joyn with his forces in <hi>Hungary,</hi> reſolving to carry on the War on that ſide with all imaginable vigour.</p>
            <p>About this time notice was given that the <hi>Turks</hi> were building 50 Boats and ſmall Veſſels near <hi>Buda,</hi> and an 100 at <hi>Belgrade</hi> and <hi>Fffeck,</hi> to bridge over the <hi>Danube,</hi> and tranſport Proviſion and Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munition as occaſion ſhould require, and the <hi>Seignior Hoſſinon</hi> who was ſent by his Imperial Majeſty to treat with Count <hi>Teckly</hi> about a Ceſſation in order to a Peace, returned without being able to ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect any thing, declaring that the ſaid <hi>Count,</hi> upon an order received from the <hi>Grand Seignior,</hi> had not only broken off the Treaty, but was with all diligence raiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing what forces he could to proſecute the War, ſo that all hopes of accommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation vaniſhed, he expecting daily a great power of <hi>Turks</hi> and <hi>Tartars</hi> to joyn
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:35052:20"/>him; to prevent which, Orders were given to break down the great Bridges over the <hi>Danube,</hi> and in their ſtead to bridge it with boats.</p>
            <p>Notwithſtanding the preparations of <hi>Teckely</hi> to take the field, yet the better to excuſe himſelf of his acting againſt the Emperor after ſo many Conceſſions and ſo much Grace offered, he, before the break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up of the Diet at <hi>Caſchaw</hi> made this Oration, <hi>viz.</hi> That what he had done was for the maintaining of their Liberties and Religions, and that he had under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gone many dangers which he could not have borne out againſt ſo potent a Prince had he not been aſſiſted by the <hi>Otta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> forces, yet with the knowledge and approbation of the Vizier of <hi>Buda</hi> he had ſome time paſt made a Ceſſation with the Emperor, and ever ſince uſed his utmoſt endeavours to continue a Peace between him and the <hi>Grand Seignior.</hi> And that therein the <hi>Grand Seignior</hi> on his part had accepted his mediation, and that for compleating it he intended nothing more than to ſend Deputies to treat with ſuch as his Imperial Majeſty ſhould ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point, as alſo to the Port to diſpoſe the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:35052:21"/>
               <hi>Grand Seignior</hi> to a more ready compli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, but that the Proteſtants ought to be reſtored to the Churches they have been diſpoſſeſſed of, and the Eſtates muſt think of a way to raiſe 40000 Crowns, which according to a late treaty with the <hi>Grand Seignior</hi> are to be paid him annual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by way of tribute; and to make pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion for the Troops he ſhould be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged to keep on foot, for the ſervice of that Kingdom and do homage to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf as Prince of the upper <hi>Hungary,</hi> and for ſuch as refuſed to ſubmit thereto, it was beſt for them for their own Safety to retire out of the Countrey. Upon which moſt of the Nobility acknowledged him as Prince of upper <hi>Hungary;</hi> and to make himſelf the more abſolute, he cauſed mony with his Effiges and Inſcription to be coined, and paſs as current through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out that Territory, to which he lays claim, by the approbation and confirmation of the <hi>Baſſa</hi> of <hi>Offen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Upon his acknowledgment <hi>Teckely</hi> ſent his Ambaſſador to the Port, as he had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore determined, and to accompany him the Eſtates choſe for their Deputy the <hi>Seiur Szirmai,</hi> who had in his inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:35052:21"/>given him by the Eſtates, theſe words, <hi>viz</hi> That the Kingdom of <hi>Hunga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> which had been reduced to a low and miſerable Eſtate, was now, by the Bleſſing of God upon the Indefatigable endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours of Count <hi>Teckely</hi> and by the favour and protection of the Port, happily re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſtabliſhed; and withall commanded him to make a due acknowledgment thereof to the <hi>Grand Seignior</hi> and his Miniſters.</p>
            <p>Theſe proceedings greatly holding all men in ſuſpence, the <hi>Swiſs Cantons</hi> ſent to the Emperor to offer him two thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand men at their own charge, and upon his requeſt gave him leave to levy forces at his own charge within their Territo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, whilſt frequent councils were held at <hi>Vienna,</hi> where the Emperor for the moſt part was preſent, for the management of the Summers War, all hopes of Ceſſation or Accomodation being laid aſide; for by this time the <hi>Turks</hi> began to be abroad in conſiderable Bodies, a Party of which made a deſcent upon the Iſle of <hi>Schuts,</hi> where they burnt a Village, killed about 30 perſons, and carryed into miſerable captivity about 100 more.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Turk</hi> reſolved upon the war; yet
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:35052:22"/>fearing the Emperour's conjunction with <hi>Poland,</hi> uſed many indeavours to avert the Diet of that Kingdom from conſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thereto; and finding fair means would not work upon them, he ſent a Chians, who on the 26 of <hi>March</hi> 1683, demanded paſſage through that King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom for 50000 <hi>Tartars,</hi> who, as he ſaid, were on their march to attend the <hi>Grand Seignior</hi> upon his arrival in <hi>Hungary,</hi> threatning them both if they refuſe or enter into Alliance with his Imperial Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, though the Diet gave ſmall regard to what he delivered, reſolving to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed in complying with the demands of the Emperor, and to conclude the treaty with Count <hi>Walſtin</hi> the Imperial Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſador.</p>
            <p>Affairs thus ſtanding, a miſunder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding happened between Count <hi>Tecke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> and the Baſſa of <hi>Buda,</hi> the latter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting to have a Gate of <hi>Caſchaw</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered to ſuch <hi>Jamzaries</hi> as he ſhould ſend thither, as likewiſe to have the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour of <hi>Villeck,</hi> whom the Count held priſoner ſince the taking of that place; both which <hi>Teckely</hi> refuſed: but in the end the difference was concluded,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:35052:22"/>which elſe might have redounded to the advantage of the Imperialiſts.</p>
            <p>The long expected Alliance with the Crown of <hi>Poland</hi> being fully agreed and concluded, the League offenſive and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſive was ſigned on the firſt of <hi>April</hi> 1683. by Count <hi>Walſtin</hi> his Imperial Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties Ambaſſador on the one part, and by the Commiſſioners of the Kingdom of <hi>Poland</hi> on the other; by which treaty the Emperor obliges himſelf to act with an Army of 60000 Horſe and Foot a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Turks,</hi> and the King of <hi>Poland</hi> is thereby obliged to have 40000 men in the field to aſſiſt the Emperor in the War, of which the Diet have approved, notwithſtanding the Threats of the <hi>Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> that the <hi>Tartars</hi> with a Body of 70000 men will fall into that King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and uſe there all manner of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtilities.</p>
            <p>The further particulars of this treaty are theſe, beſides the forces aforeſaid, either Potentare is obliged to have in the field, the Emperor is to pay the <hi>Polonian</hi> King in preſent Money Twelve Thouſand Flor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rins, and that his Imperial Majeſty and the Queen Dowager of <hi>Poland,</hi>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:35052:23"/>do relinquiſh all pretenſions of right they have or might have to the Crown of <hi>Poland,</hi> and that neither the Emperor nor King of <hi>Poland</hi> do enter into a treaty or conclude a Peace with the <hi>Grand Seignior</hi> without each others Approbation and Conſent.</p>
            <p>The time for Action drawing nigh, a great Council of war was held at <hi>Vienna</hi> on the <hi>9th</hi> of <hi>April</hi> 1683, in order to take ſuch meaſures as might be advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geous to the Empire in this Summers Campaign; upon whoſe ſitting, the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grave of <hi>Baden,</hi> whom the Emperor had ſent to take a view of <hi>Commora, Raab,</hi> the Iſle of <hi>Schuts,</hi> and other places of impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, arrived and made his report, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring in what condition the fortifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions were, and in how good a poſture of defence; after which the Council pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded to appoint the place of Rendezvous for the Army to be at <hi>Presburg,</hi> and to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove of the Emperors choice in nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nating the Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er in chief of his Army, to be imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed againſt the <hi>Turks,</hi> and reſolved that it was convenient and altogether neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary that a Body of men ſhould be kept in
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:35052:23"/>pay in <hi>Crotia,</hi> under the command of the Viceroy, the better to ſecure thoſe Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, from the incurſion of the <hi>Turks</hi> and <hi>Tartars,</hi> who were rallying on that ſide to burn and plunder. They further con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded, that it was convenient that Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral <hi>Schuts</hi> ſhould immediatly march with 7000 men to joyn with the Prince <hi>Lubomirski,</hi> who was advanced with 6000 Poliſh Horſe for the ſervice of the Emperor, and that the Hungarian Troops conſiſting of a body of 2500 Horſe and Foot Joyning with them, ſhould Act upon the <hi>Waag,</hi> to prevent the <hi>Turks</hi> and Rebels from joyning, and to hinder any Incurſion that otherwiſe might be made. That another body of 6000 men ſhould incamp on the <hi>Waag</hi> near <hi>Leopolstat,</hi> and in caſe they perceive the <hi>Turks</hi> to have a deſign up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that place, to put themſelves into it: and beſides this, it was further ordered, that ten or twelve thouſand men ſhould be poſted upon the Frontiers of <hi>Morovia</hi> and <hi>Sileſia</hi> to ſecure thoſe Countries a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the incurſion of the <hi>Turks.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Spring being now far advanced, Count <hi>Teckely</hi> impatient of longer lying
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:35052:24"/>ſtill, having drawn his Troops under the Walls of <hi>Caſchaw,</hi> diſpatcht a Meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger to the Baſſa of <hi>Buda</hi> for a ſupply of 5000 horſe, that ſo he might invade the Country of <hi>Silecia;</hi> with which num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber he was ſupplied, and at the ſame time he ſent his Mandates to the Nobility of the upper <hi>Hungary,</hi> to attend him in Armes as their Prince; but moſt of them ſent their excuſes, deſiring him not to involve them in ſuch Danger and Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard, but rather accept a Sum of Money in Lieu of their ſervice, the which, of ſome he accepted, but of others refuſed, ſaying, they ſecretly envied his Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, and held correſpondency with the <hi>Imperialiſts,</hi> therefore he thought it not good to truſt them out of his ſight, threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning them with Military Execution if they did not inſtantly repair to his Stan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dard.</p>
            <p>The King of <hi>Poland</hi> being haſtened by the Imperial Miniſter reſiding at his Court, upon the concluſion of the Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſive and Defenſive League, uſed ſuch diligence in raiſing men for the Service of the War, and ſummoning the Ban and Arrear-ban of that Kingdom to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:35052:24"/>him on the 20th of <hi>May,</hi> he mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtered an Army of 35000 men near <hi>Leo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pol,</hi> with a deſign immediately to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vade <hi>Caminice,</hi> a ſtrong Place taken from the <hi>Turks,</hi> who about two Years ſince ſurprized it, but at this time was diverted, upon notice that the Fore-run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of the <hi>Turks</hi> Army were arrived at <hi>Belgrade,</hi> and that the Grand <hi>Vizier</hi> was but four days march behind, with a Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of 60000 Men, and that 25000 <hi>Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars</hi> had paſſed the <hi>Neister;</hi> yet he ſent to Count <hi>Teckely</hi> to acquaint him that he had made an Offenſive and Defenſive League with the Emperor, and to let him know, that unleſs he immediatly made his Peace with his Imperial Majeſty, he ſhould be obliged to treat him as his Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, to which the Count returned Anſwer, that he had uſed his endeavour at the Port for an Accommodation, but found the <hi>Grand Seignior</hi> altogether averſe thereto; and that without his Conſent he could not, neither would, enter upon any fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Treaty, or conclude a Peace, he having plighted his Faith to the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry: therefore if his Majeſty of <hi>Poland</hi> did invade his Territories, he would do
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:35052:25"/>his utmoſt to defend them, and oppoſe the Invader with all his Power; and thereupon gave Order for the paſſing ſix thouſand Horſe and Foot over the <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nube,</hi> to joyn a Body of <hi>Turks</hi> that wer eco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming down, who in Conjunction are to have an Eye upon that part of the upper <hi>Hungary,</hi> bordering on the Territories of the King of <hi>Poland,</hi> and ſent out di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers Convoys to fetch in Corn and other Proviſion into his Camp, reſolving to expect the coming of the Grand Vizier, whilſt in the mean time the Palatine of <hi>Hungary</hi> and Vice-roy of <hi>Crotia,</hi> were drawing the Forces of thoſe Countries in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a Body to joyn the <hi>Imperialiſts,</hi> who daily repaired to the place of Rendez vouz.</p>
            <p>Theſe things paſſing, the Treaty be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Emperour and the Elector of <hi>Brandenburg,</hi> was preſſed by the Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial Miniſter reſiding at that Court, with all earneſtneſs, to which his Electoral Highneſs appeared no way averſe, but deſired time to conſider what Methods he ſhould take in order to his raiſing and maintaining ſuch Forces as was on the part of the Emperour required, to
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:35052:25"/>aſſiſt him in his Wars againſt the <hi>Turk,</hi> which gave all men hopes of what after enſued, <hi>viz.</hi> That an offenſive and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſie League would be the conſequence of that Treaty.</p>
            <p>The 6th of <hi>May</hi> being come, his Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perial Majeſty, accompanied with the Duke of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> the Elector of <hi>Bavaria,</hi> and other Princes of the Empire, came to <hi>Presburg,</hi> to take a view of the Army, and to ſee them drawn up into Battalia, and exerciſe in warlike Diſcipline: the Liſt of which Forces, as it was publiſhed, running thus.</p>
            <p>According to the Liſt taken by the Command of the Duke of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> the Emperour has in Pay twenty ſeven Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giments of Foot, making together 55700 Men whereof 25296 were at the general Rendezvouſe near <hi>Presburg,</hi> 4692 in the upper <hi>Hungar,</hi> 2040 in <hi>Jabulunca</hi> on the Frontier of <hi>Hungary,</hi> 2040 at <hi>Leopolſtade</hi> on the <hi>Waag,</hi> 364 in <hi>Auſtria,</hi> 2040 at <hi>Vienna,</hi> 13912 in the Empire, and 2040 in <hi>Bohemia.</hi> In the Emperour's Pay is likewiſe ſeventeen Regiments of Horſe, amounting to 13600 Men, ſeven Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Dragoons, conſiſting of 5600
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:35052:26"/>Men, and four Regiments of <hi>Croats</hi> conſiſting of 3200 Men, whereof 15200 are at the General Rendezvouz, 800 in the upper <hi>Hungary,</hi> 400 in <hi>Jabulunca,</hi> 2400 at <hi>Leopalſtadt,</hi> 800 in <hi>Auſtria,</hi> and 2800 in the Empire. So that the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Liſt of Horſe and Foot appears to be thus, at the gencral Rendezvouz 39696, in the Empire 16712, in the up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per <hi>Hungary</hi> 7532, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> in all making 78540 Men, Horſe and Foot, not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counting the Troops under the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of the Palatine of <hi>Hungary,</hi> nor thoſe commanded by the Vice-Roy of <hi>Crotia,</hi> nor the 600 <hi>Poliſh</hi> horſe brought into the ſervice of the Emperour by the Prince <hi>Lubomirski,</hi> over the Army in <hi>Hungary,</hi> or to Act there againſt the <hi>Turks, Tartars,</hi> and Rebells.</p>
            <p>The Emperour appointed the Duke of <hi>Lorrain Generaliſſimo,</hi> impowering him to Act as he ſaw occaſion, for the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage of the Empire, without expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any orders from Court, unleſs upon ſpecial occaſion, declaring his reſolution to carry on the War with all imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable vigout, hoping the Princes of the Empire and other Chriſtian Princes,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:35052:26"/>would freely imbarque themſelves in the Action, ſeeing it not only concerned the Empire, but indeed all Chriſtendom; For that the Grand Seignior aided not his Rebels for pity ſake, as he gave out, but took hold of the opportunity to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>croach upon the Chriſtian Princes, and if poſſible, to over-run all Chriſtendom; which he hoped God would never per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to fall into the hands of ſo cruel and unmerciful an Infidel.</p>
            <p>This diſcourſe ended, the Emperour ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſhed ſuch chief Commanders as were preſent to play the man, ſaying, that he would be always ready to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the Valiant, and with the ſame Willingneſs puniſh the Coward. Aſter which he rode about the Camp to take a view of the Order of his Men, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed himſelf highly ſatisfied in their Promptneſs and Aptneſs to handle their Arms and manage them at all Points; and then having taken leave of the Duke, he returned to <hi>Vienna.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>About the latter end of <hi>April,</hi> the Grand Seignior ſet forth from <hi>Adrianople,</hi> in order to his being preſent at the Ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dezvouz to be holden for the Summers
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:35052:27"/>Campaign near <hi>Belgrade;</hi> the manner of his ſetting forward and Attendance being thus</p>
            <p>Firſt, his Tents or rich Pavillions were carried to the Place, where, the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing Night, he deſigned to lodge, then went the Carriages with other Tents, for the Commanders and Souldiers; for note, that the <hi>Turks</hi> have always dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Tents, or twice ſo many as is needful to lodge in, the Reaſon being this; when the Tents are pitched in which they intend to incamp, the other Tents are carried and pitched a days Journey before; ſo that when they riſe again, they, upon their Arrival at the place where they are to lodge, find their Tents ready, which is one great help to them in their ſwift Marches; but in caſe they are in an Enemies Country, and march but ſlowly, this Order is not obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved.</p>
            <p>The firſt Day, the Army conſiſting of 180000 Men marched twenty five <hi>Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiſh</hi> miles, and at Night pitching their Tents, ſeemed rather a City than a Field Proviſion; for about the Tents of the <hi>Grand Seignior</hi> were thoſe of the <hi>Baſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſas</hi>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:35052:27"/>and great Commanders; next them, more outward, thoſe of leſſer rank, and ſo by degrees, according to their Quality or Merit in Arms. As for the Order of the Grand Seignior's March, it was thus; Before the Body of the Army went the Yeomen, a kind of Foot-men, much in the nature of Pioniers, who cleared the way, and levelled the ground for the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and more convenient Paſſage of the Carriages, ſetting up heaps of Stones and other ſigns as marks, and ſetting Fire to divers Piles of Wood at the beginning of the Match; for obſerve, the <hi>Turks</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways (unleſs ſomething extraordinary prevent it) begin their March at Mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>night, and ſo continue to march till the Noon of the enſuing Day. Between two Baſſas of his Council rode the Grand Seignior, with a ſhort Turlipant, his Turbant ſet with Diamonds, and his Tunick or Veſt ſtudded o're with Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bies, Emeralds, and Saphires, his Hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes Bridle of Gold, and in his Fore-head a blazing Carbuncle, his Bridle bit Gold, and Stirrops of the ſame Mettal: before him marched the <hi>Janizaries,</hi> as likewiſe on either ſide, the foremoſt being on
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:35052:28"/>Horſeback bearing lighted torches, and the reſt on Foot armed with Harquibuſſes and Pole-axes with very ſhort Handles; but between them and the Grand Seig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nior marched divers Captains, with Horſemens Maces to keep the Vulgar from gazing on the Emperour; and nearer to his Perſon marched a thouſand of his Guards, called the <hi>Ich Oglians,</hi> or young Gentlemen brought up in the <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raglio,</hi> till ſuch time they are fit for Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, being before-hand inſtructed in all manner of Feats of War, as ſhooting the Harquibuſs, caſting Darts, uſing the Long-bow, toſſing the Launce or Pike, uſing the Mace, and the like; and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately after him, within this Circle, marched divers of the Officers of the <hi>Seraglio,</hi> being for the moſt part Eunuchs, and in the midſt of them a Chariot or cloſe Litter, in which were the Women for the <hi>Grand Seignior</hi>'s Uſe; and in each Wing of the Army, or Points of the Creſcent, were divers other Chariots or Litters filled with Women, appertaining to the Baſſas, or great Captains, not exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing twenty; for the moſt part their Wives, tho formerly no ſuch thing was permitted.
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:35052:28"/>Theſe were incloſed with the divers Orders, as the <hi>Tamaru,</hi> which are Men on horſeback, bearing Lances and Scemyters, who are at all times bound to ſerve in the Wars in lieu of certain Lands they hold of the <hi>Grand Seig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nior</hi> throughout his dominion. The <hi>Accanzi,</hi> another ſort of Horſemen, who are kept in continual Pay, and are reckoned, for horſe, the chiefeſt ſtrength of the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Empire, as the <hi>Janizaries,</hi> who are compoſed of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian tributary Children, are account<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed its ſtrength for Foot; and the <hi>Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſapi,</hi> who are of ſmall account, being the Refuſe of the Empire, who ſerve only for Plunder, Marching on Foot, and are, for the moſt part, in Battels, thruſt ſorward as the forlorn hope, on no other account than to blunt the Enemies Swords; or in Seiges, driven upon the mouth of the murthering Cannons, to no other end than to fill up the Trenches and Ditches with their dead bodies, that ſo the Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious <hi>Janizaries</hi> may mount the ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſier on the Ramparts, or Walls of
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:35052:29"/>the Place beſieged: and theſe, for the moſt part, are the Sons of <hi>Turks.</hi> Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter theſe marched the Camels, Mules, Dromedaries, and Sumpters, with all manner of proviſions; as likewiſe, Taylors, Bakers, Butchers, Sutlers, and indeed, all men of Trades that can poſſibly depend upon an Army, or who by labour, or procuring Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion can be any ways ſerviceable: ſo that where ever the Tents are pitched all Trades pitch round about them; In ſo much that the Camp ſeems ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther like a Mart or Fair than an ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Hoſt, with Banners. All the way they marched in the poſture a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid, they kept deep ſilence, even to admiration, not offering to break Ranks, or, as little as poſſible, to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damage the Orchards, Fields, or Gardens, as they paſſed: and when they came to pitch as aforeſaid, all of them, with a loud yell or ſinging tone, cryed, Allali, Allah, Allahu, which is thrice repeating, <hi>O God,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Thus the Army continued in its march till it came to the General
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:35052:29"/>Rendeſvouz, therefore the particulars of each days march I ſhall wave for brevities ſake, and again by following the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Army, return into <hi>Hunga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> where great preparations, on all ſides, were made for a vigorous proſecution of the War. The <hi>Tartars</hi> barbarous Troops beginning to ravage the Country near <hi>Caminice,</hi> Plundring, Burning, and ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king Captive all that came in their way, driving before them the wretched peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple naked, and bound together with Cords in great droves: to oppoſe whom the <hi>Poloman</hi> King drew down fifteen thouſand Horſe and Foot, ſending to the <hi>Coſſacks</hi> to take the Field, and joyn him, promiſing them large Pay, and at the ſame time ſtrictly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding his Subjects not to have any intercourſe with the <hi>Hungarian</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bells upon ſevere Penalties; and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all ſent an Envoy to Count <hi>Teckely</hi> to move him with many pregnant rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons and perſwaſive Arguments to a complyance and a ſubmiſſion to the propoſals of his Imperial Majeſty: but the ſaid Envoy prevailed not with his perverſe nature, but as it were rendred
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:35052:30"/>him more haughty and obſtinate, by ſuppoſing his Ceſſation would be pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed at any rate; ſince Emperours and Kings, as it were, became ſo deſirous of his Friendſhip.</p>
            <p>Things being brought to this paſs, his Imperial Majeſty continued to chear his Commanders and Souldiers with his Preſence, and to give Orders for their taking the Field; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon he, accompanied with the Arch Dutcheſs, and Elector of <hi>Bava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria,</hi> took another view of the Camp, lying near the Walls of <hi>Presburg,</hi> and was received with all Joy imaginable: the Army againſt his coming being drawn up into Batalia in two lines, at leaſt an <hi>Hungarian</hi> Mile in length, and eighty peices of Cannon, Demy Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non, and Culvering placed at the Head of it, whereas about eleven of the Clock the Biſhop of <hi>Strigonia</hi> ſung Maſs in a Tent for that purpoſe prepared, in which for the Emperour and Empreſs was a ſeat ſet, Canopied over with Cloath of Gold, another for the Arch Dutcheſs, and a third for the Elector of <hi>Bavaria</hi> and Duke of <hi>Lorain</hi>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:35052:30"/>the Maſs ended, the Biſhop came from under the Tent, and bleſſed the Army, whenas the Emperour mount<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on Horſe-back, and being follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Empreſs, Arch-Dutcheſs, Elector of <hi>Bavaria,</hi> and divers others of the Nobility, he viſited the Ranks, ſtill encouraging, with his Preſence and Speeches, the Souldiers and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manders, to do their utmoſt againſt the common Enemy, and then return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to a ſtately Tent, prepared by the Duke of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> in which the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, Empreſs, Arch-Ducheſs, Elector of <hi>Bavaria,</hi> Duke of <hi>Saxe Lawenburg,</hi> and Prince <hi>Louis</hi> of <hi>Baden,</hi> were ſplen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>didly entertained at Dinner: divers other Tables in Tents, ſpread for that purpoſe, being furniſhed for the other Nobility attending them; and in the mean time the whole tire of Artille<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry was thrice diſcharged, and the whole Army, to which his Imperial Majeſty, for the better encouragement of the Officers and Souldiers, gave a Months Pay, upon free giſt, gave three Salvo's of ſmall ſhot, and ſo his Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:35052:31"/>Majeſty, with the reſt of the Court, returned to <hi>Presburg,</hi> and from thence to <hi>Vienna,</hi> having given what neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary Orders he conceived convenient; and amongſt other things, that twelve half Cannon and eight great Mortar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pieces ſhould be taken out of the <hi>Arſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal,</hi> and ſent to the Army, which had received a Command to march and oppoſe the Proceedings of <hi>Teckely,</hi> who by this time was very active on this ſide the <hi>Waag:</hi> the Imperial Army upon muſter was found to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mount to 47000 men.</p>
            <p>Upon the remove of the Army, News came that a <hi>Croatian</hi> Souldier, having inſinuated himſelf into great credit and confidence with the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Governour of <hi>Ziget,</hi> had watched his opportunity to fire the Magazine of the Garriſon, which was capable of main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining 30000 men for the ſpace of two Years, and that being made Store<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe-keeper, in one part of the ſaid Magazine he had ſet fire to it by a train, and blown up all, making his eſcape into <hi>Croatia</hi> whilſt the conſterna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:35052:31"/>laſted; and that by the fall of tim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, and blow of Powder, not only moſt of the Houſes were demoliſhed, but Five Hundred <hi>Turks</hi> killed.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Turks</hi> by this time having drawn a Body of twenty five thouſand men under the Walls of <hi>New-Huſel,</hi> Major General <hi>Schutz,</hi> with a ſtrong Party of <hi>Imperials, Hungarians,</hi> and <hi>Bohemians,</hi> was ſent out to obſerve their motion: who, upon notice from the Countrey People thereabout, that a Party of <hi>Turkiſh</hi> forragers belonging to the ſaid Garriſon, were abroad, and had done great Miſchief by burning Houſes, driving away Cattel, and ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king Priſoners, and that they were up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their return with a conſiderable Booty, he taking Guides, marched croſs the Countrey with a thouſand Foot and five hundred Horſe, found them encamped upon a great Plain near <hi>Tranchin,</hi> who little ſuſpecting any of the Imperial Troops had paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the <hi>Waag,</hi> lay careleſly diſperſed; inſomuch that being furiouſly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countred, though they could not be
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:35052:32"/>leſs in number than two thouſand five hundred, yet they were put to flight and exceeding great ſlaughter; inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that ſeven hundred fell by the Sword, and two hundred were drown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the River, divers Priſoners of note taken, and all the Booty recover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, with the loſs only of fifty Imperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als, twelve Hungarians, and amongſt them one Captain, two Enſign-bearers, and a Major of Horſe.</p>
            <p>The King of <hi>Poland</hi> perceiving the <hi>Tartarian</hi> Forces to increaſe, and upon his Frontiers commit divers Outrages, the better to inforce himſelf, thought not only fit at his proper Charge to raiſe two Regiments, one for the Queen, and the other for Prince <hi>Alexander,</hi> his eldeſt Son, but delivered out of the Treaſury of his hereditary Eſtate a hundred thouſand Crowns, towards the providing a greater Train of Artillery, and defraying the Charges of the War; with part of which he raiſed eight hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred <hi>Huſſars</hi> armed with Launces, and ſtrictly to guard the Confines of <hi>Sileſia,</hi> on which the <hi>Tartar</hi> Cham had a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:35052:32"/>to make Deſcent, giving it out that he deſigned nothing more than to take the Spoil of that Province.</p>
            <p>By this time the Imperial Army was arrived at <hi>Ketſer,</hi> and riſing from thence, marched towards <hi>Raab,</hi> under the command of the Duke of <hi>Lorram,</hi> as <hi>Generaliſſimus,</hi> the Right Wing of Horſe commanded by the Duke of <hi>Saxe-Lawenburg,</hi> and the Left by Count <hi>Caprara,</hi> Count <hi>Staremberg</hi> being Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral of the Foot, and ſo Marching along the Banks of the <hi>Waag,</hi> came and incamped between <hi>Raab</hi> and <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mora,</hi> to expect the motion of the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my; and there it was that the Duke had the firſt notice of the Grand <hi>Viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers</hi> advancing with the groſs of the <hi>Ot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toman</hi> Army, as far as <hi>Greicks Wiſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berg,</hi> and that the Grand Seignior with a greater Power followed by ſlow Marches, having vowed not to turn his back till he had beſieged with his Army the City of <hi>Vienna,</hi> the principal Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perial Seat of <hi>Auſtria;</hi> upon notice of which the Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> again decamped, after he had ſent the Count
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:35052:33"/>
               <hi>Palfie</hi> to give the Emperour an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of the State of the War, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolving to be in Action, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon marched towards <hi>Gran,</hi> a ſtrong Garriſon of the <hi>Turks</hi> in <hi>Hungaria,</hi> with a deſign to beſiege it; for that purpoſe having ſent for divers other Mortars, Granadoes Bombes, and the like; they were ſent up the River in Boats and arrived ſafely at the Camp.</p>
            <p>The Emperour finding the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſeneſs of the <hi>Hungarian</hi> Rebels, ſent an expreſs to the <hi>Palatine</hi> of that King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, immediately to march with the Forces under his Command, not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mounting to above five thouſand, with which he had been poſted in the Iſle of <hi>Schuts,</hi> to joyn Major General <hi>Schuts</hi> and the Prince <hi>Lubomirski,</hi> on the <hi>Waag,</hi> and there to act againſt Count <hi>Teckely,</hi> and ſuch Forces as he had in the Field; who at that time beſieged the Caſtle of <hi>Donowitz,</hi> but before they could draw together ſtrong enough to raiſe the Siege, the ſaid Caſtle was, after five weeks Siege, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:35052:33"/>and the Baron <hi>Joannel,</hi> Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour thereof, made Priſoner; yet <hi>Teckely</hi> began to grow jealous of the <hi>Turks;</hi> who now having, by his Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion, made way for their Arms, did not regard him as before; therefore, although the <hi>Baſſa</hi> of <hi>Offen</hi> ſent divers Summons to command him to joyn his Forces with the Body of <hi>Turks,</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>camped near new <hi>Huſel,</hi> yet he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clined it, making divers excuſes and deſiring that he might act ſeparate.</p>
            <p>That nothing might be wanting in the Emperour to prevent the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries of War in the ſo long diſtract<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Kingdom of <hi>Hungary,</hi> but that thoſe that had taken up Rebellious Arms againſt him might eaſily per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive how willing he was for the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the effuſion of Chriſtian Blood, to forget and forgive what was paſt, he again publiſhed a General Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, promiſing thereby, as well to the <hi>Hungarians,</hi> as <hi>Germans,</hi> who had been or are in Rebellion againſt him, reſtitution of, Goods and Eſtates, if they lay down their Arms, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:35052:34"/>to their Obedience: upon which ſeveral <hi>Germans</hi> and ſome <hi>Hunga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians,</hi> who had deſerted the Emperours Service, and taken part with Rebels, came in and ſubmitted, who there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon were reſtored in Perſon, Goods and Eſtates; which did not a little alarm Count <hi>Teckely,</hi> by poſſeſſing him with a Fear that many of his Fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers might do the like; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon to prevent it, he again began a feigned Treaty with the Emperour; and the rather, for that he had no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice that the <hi>Czar</hi> of <hi>Muſcovy</hi> earneſtly deſired to enter into the Treaty be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Emperour and King of <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land:</hi> yet he put a ſtrong Garriſon in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Fortreſs of <hi>Donowitz,</hi> which is a Place of great Importance, and ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of puting all the Country under Contribution as far as <hi>Cracow.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> with the Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial Army being advanced within four Leagues of <hi>Gran,</hi> incamped there, to expect an Account in what poſture the Enemies were; as not thinking it ſafe to beſiege ſo Important a Place as
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:35052:34"/>
               <hi>Gran,</hi> without good aſſurance: and there he received advice, that the Grand <hi>Viſier</hi> and <hi>Aga</hi> of the <hi>Janiza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries</hi> were with all diligence forming the Body of their Army near <hi>Belgrave,</hi> whereupon he ſent out two Parties, each conſiſting of four thouſand Men, to obſerve their motion, he alſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived advice that the Count <hi>Caprara,</hi> his Imperial Majeſties Ambaſſador, who ſo long negotiated at the Port, was brought to <hi>Belgrave,</hi> under the charge of the <hi>Aga</hi> of <hi>Janizaries,</hi> and ſtrictly guarded, not permitted to go abroad without eſpecial Licence from the Grand <hi>Viſier,</hi> and then not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out fifty <hi>Janizaries</hi> to attend him, to whom he is obliged to pay a daily Stipend.</p>
            <p>The Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> having learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the State of the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Army, and ſent out a Party who defeated eight hundred <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Horſe that were ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced near his Camp to diſcover what they could, raiſed his Camp, and marched directly towards <hi>New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>huſel,</hi> not thinking it ſafe to attempt
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:35052:35"/>
               <hi>Gran,</hi> in which Garriſon there was not computed to be leſs than eight thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand <hi>Turks,</hi> and <hi>Hungarians:</hi> but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolving to be in action before the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of the Turkiſh Army could take the Field, although he had frequent advice that the Grand <hi>Viſier</hi> ſent out daily Detachments, and amongſt the reſt one very conſiderable, conſiſting of twenty thouſand Men, to joyn the <hi>Baſſa</hi> of <hi>Buda;</hi> he ſat down before <hi>New-huſel,</hi> the greateſt part of whoſe Suburbs the Garriſon had demoliſhed and burnt, as not being Tenable, and retired into the City or upper Town, at what time the Country-People in the Turkiſh Territories near <hi>Commora</hi> and <hi>Raab,</hi> fearing the advance of the Turkiſh Army, retired with their Subſtance into thoſe Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial Garriſons, to prevent the ſevere Treatments which they are wont to receive from the, Turks in times of War, and with all poſſible diligence the great Ordnance were conveyed to the Camp, whilſt a Body of Men was forming at <hi>Presburg</hi> to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cruit
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:35052:35"/>the Emperours Army if occaſion required it, being compoſed of <hi>Mora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vians, Bohemians,</hi> and <hi>Hungarians,</hi> and to prevent any Party that might be ſent from the Enemies Camp falling upon his Out-guards, he ſent a Detach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of ſour thouſand Horſe in two Parties to burn the Bridge of <hi>Eſſek;</hi> where, upon their Arrival, they found ſeven hundred <hi>Turks</hi> advantagiouſly poſted, who at firſt made great ſhews to defend the ſaid Bridge; but upon the firſt Diſcharge of four Field-pieces the Imperialiſts brought with them, the <hi>Turks</hi> in great Diſorder retired, as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together deſpairing to defend it, yet not ſo ſwiftly, but being purſued, about a hundred of them were killed, and as many taken Priſoners; when after the Diſpute, the Priſoners, to the number of two hundred, who for that purpoſe brought Saws, Axes, Sleds, and the like, broke the Bridge in pieces, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward burnt the greateſt part, ſetting the reſt a float down the River.</p>
            <p>By this time the Duke having in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trenched and raiſed his Battery, play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:35052:36"/>furiouſly upon the Town with eight piece of Canon, carrying thirty ſix and forty pound Balls, and was anſwered in the ſame Language by the beſieged, who made diverſe Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies to hinder the advancement of the Lines and Works, wherein divers were killed on either ſide: for in the Town were, amongſt others, a thouſand <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nizaries,</hi> two or three hundred of which were in every Sally that was made, for the ſpace of four days, in which ſpace ſix Sallies were made, though with the greateſt diſadvantage to the <hi>Turks,</hi> for the <hi>Imperialiſts</hi> keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in their Trenches, cut divers of the Enemies in pieces as they came to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tacque them. Upon notice of this Siege, the Baſſa of <hi>Offen</hi> ſent to the Duke to inform him, that the <hi>Grand Seignior</hi> and Count <hi>Teckely</hi> were reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to obſerve the Truce till it expi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red; but he returned anſwer, that they had by divers Hoſtilities, as well the <hi>Turks</hi> as the <hi>Hungarian</hi> Rebells, broke the Truce, and that this offer he could conceive to no other end th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:35052:36"/>time till they could draw their Army into the field: therefore he found it abſolutely neceſſary, ſince they had been the Aggreſſors, to make the beſt uſe of the preſent Juncture, to employ the Arms of the Empire to the beſt advantage, and that he could not hearken to the obſerving a Truce that the Enemy had ſo manifeſtly violated, but if he had any thing to offer in that Caſe, he muſt apply himſelf to the Emperour, and the Council of War, aſſembled to debate the reaſonableneſs of ſuch Matters: and with this An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer the Meſſenger being diſpatched, he cauſed two pieces of Cannon, new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly arrived in the Camp, carrying Balls of fifty and ſixty pound, to be bent againſt the Gate, looking towards <hi>Gran,</hi> and battering it with ſixteen ſhot, beat in pieces the Iron Port-cullices and Ribs of Copper, but the beſieged had countermured, or rather dammed it up, yet a furious aſſault was given, but without ſucceſs; for the <hi>Imperialiſts</hi> were capable of entring, but with ſome loſs obliged to retire, though divers
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:35052:37"/>freſh Parties were commanded on: For the Turks from a Sally-Port, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſcerned by the Chriſtians, came down upon them in great numbers, yet they made good their ground with a bloody and doubtful Fight, till the <hi>Turks</hi> were beaten into the Town, and the Retreat ſounded by command to call off the <hi>Imperials.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But leaving this Siege a while, I ſhall return to Count <hi>Teckely,</hi> who, continuing near <hi>Tokay,</hi> drew together ſuch Forces as he could to oppoſe the Joynt-Forces under the Leading of the Prince <hi>Lubomirski,</hi> the Palatine of <hi>Hungary,</hi> and Major General <hi>Schutz,</hi> who had ſeized the important Poſts on the <hi>Waag,</hi> and by that means hinder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him from joyning with the <hi>Turks,</hi> at which, as moſt ſuppoſe, he was no whit ſorry, but rather rejoyced at ſuch an excuſe; for had he been embodied with the Turkiſh Army, his Grandeur, by which he allured the ignorant, and ſuch as ſought for Prey, to take Arms againſt their Emperour, would have been ecclipſed and impaired, eſpecially
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:35052:37"/>if they had been commanded by a Turkiſh <hi>Baſſa;</hi> for ſuch is the Inſolen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of thoſe men, that although they, for the moſt part, are in their Original but Slaves or Tribute Children, that when they come to this Preferment they make no Scruple to Lord it over Kings and Princes, though their Lives and Fortunes depend upon the Breath and Pleaſure of their Maſter, who fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently, upon the leaſt <hi>Capricio,</hi> diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeiſes them both of Life and Honour, ſending the meaneſt of his Slaves for the Heads of his greateſt Captains; nor dare any other oppoſe it upon Forfei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of their own.</p>
            <p>This being a good excuſe for <hi>Tecke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> the better to keep up his Reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion with his Faction, he again pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to treat with the Emperour a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout a truce; but this Artifice ſo often uſed to protract time would not take, he thinking by another ſtratagem to pacifie the <hi>Turk,</hi> gave out he would joyn with a Body of <hi>Tartars,</hi> conſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of nine thouſand, in order to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiege <hi>Zathmor,</hi> as knowing that he
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:35052:38"/>could at pleaſure Lord it over thoſe rude People who came to Wars only for Prey, and if ſo be they can get Booty, they matter not who Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands or whom they Spoil, be he Friend or Enemy. Having joyned a Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of theſe barbarous Infidels, more in hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane than the <hi>Turks,</hi> he paſſed a Breach of the <hi>Danube,</hi> &amp; burnt divers Villages, Plundring and taking Priſoners many of the Boors, who had not time to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire, by reaſon of his ſuddain and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>expected arrival, many of thoſe mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable people fell likewiſe into the hands of the <hi>Tartars,</hi> who tying them together in cords drove them before them into miſerable boudage, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veying them thither (without any hark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ening to Ranſoms propoſed by their Friends) by ſuch Merchants, as they call them, as the Soldiers ſold them to, who for that purpoſe always attend the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Camp, bring Loads of Cords and Iron ſhackles to Bind and ſecure them, without reſpect either to Sex or Age, nay the Aged fare worſe than thoſe in the ſtrength of their Age;
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:35052:38"/>middle Age, or extraordinary Young; for they being looked upon as unſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viceable, ſeldom eſcape the Sword.</p>
            <p>To requite the outrage of <hi>Teckely</hi> and the <hi>Tartars,</hi> the Vice-roy of <hi>Cro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia</hi> having notice that a Party of the Rebels, <hi>Turks</hi> and <hi>Tartars,</hi> to the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of twelve or thirteen thouſand, were advahcing upon the Frontiers, he by ſtopping the ſtrait Paſs of <hi>Jabulunk</hi> not only impeded their advancement, but, with a party of a thouſand horſe, fell into them, and after two hours diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute put them to the rout, killing three hundred upon the place, and taking a hundred Priſoners, thereby redeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or reſcuing divers miſerable Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, whom they dragged after them in Ropes and Chains, having ſurpriſed them in their Houſes, moſt of whoſe Houſes they had plundred and laid in Aſhes.</p>
            <p>The Siege of <hi>New-Huſel,</hi> whiſt theſe things were doing, was carryed on by the Imperialiſts with all imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable Vigor, and the Beſieged prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red as reſolutly to defend it, being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:35052:39"/>thereto by the approach of the Turks Army, a part of which by this time was lodged upon an Emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence near <hi>Gran,</hi> and waited for an additional force to fall upon the forces appointed to Guard the River <hi>Nitera</hi> under the command of the Palatine of <hi>Hungary,</hi> who undertook, with a ſelect power of the Militia of that Kingdom, to defend both that and the <hi>Waag:</hi> yet ſuch was the reſolution of the Imperial Leagers that they advanced their trenches within an hundred paces of the Wall, running them under ground, in order to fix a Mine under the chief Bull-work of that Garriſon, playing at the ſame time furiouſly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Wall: inſomuch that, for the ſpace of two hundred yards, all the Battlements were beaten down; which the Turks in the Counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcarp perceiving, ſallied furiouſly upon the Pioneers; but being encountered by a Regiment of <hi>Auſtrians</hi> command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on to their aſſiſtance, they were forced to retire with the loſs of ſixty eight of their companions, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:35052:39"/>them a <hi>Zangiack,</hi> two Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains and an Enſign-bearer, when following that ſucceſs, the Imperialiſts preſſing on, entred one of their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubts, and for a while maintained it, but a great party ſallying, and the Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non of the Town playing inceſſantly upon them, they were forced to retire with ſome loſs.</p>
            <p>Theſe things paſſing, divers Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels where held at <hi>Vienna</hi> and <hi>Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burg,</hi> in order to the management of the War, the Electoral Princes being daily ſollicited to ſend ſuch Troops as they could raiſe into the Field; for that by frequent Courriers it was adviſed, that the body of the Turks Army, under the leading of the <hi>Grand Viſier,</hi> had muſtered, and was drawing from <hi>Bell-grade</hi> in order to beſiege ſome Important place, thereby to raiſe the Seige of <hi>New-huſel:</hi> whereupon it was reſolved that three new Regiments ſhould be raiſed, and that four Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments one of Horſe and an other of Foot ſhould be detached from the forces of the Empire, under the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:35052:40"/>of Count <hi>Waldeck,</hi> as likewiſe it was agreed, that the <hi>Quota</hi>'s and Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rears of the Electoral Princes, and all other Princes depending upon the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, ſhould be immediately perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, for defraying the Charges, and for the better management of the War. Upon which Reſolves, the Marqueſs of <hi>Baden Dourlach</hi> preſented his Deputy a memorial, ſetting forth the great dama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges he had ſuſtained by the War be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Empire and the Crown of <hi>France,</hi> as well by the laſt as the prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent: &amp; therefore deſired that he might be freed from the Taxes of the Empire, as not being in a capacity to pay them; upon which the Eſtates aſſembled in Council, wrote a favourable letter to the Emperour in his behalf, but the affairs of the Empire requiring great Summs of Mony to defray the charges of a wide waſting War, it could not be wholly diſpenced with, though part was remitted.</p>
            <pb n="65" facs="tcp:35052:40"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Teckely</hi> having taken breath for a long time without being urged to action, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled a great party near <hi>Zatmar,</hi> threatning to beſiege it: and to that end ſent for <hi>Han Kerogly,</hi> Commander of the <hi>Tartarian</hi> Troops in thoſe parts. Whereupon the Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> ſent a Regiment of Foot to enter it; who without any oppoſition effected the command of their General, which put a ſtop to the intention of the Rebells; yet they out of a bravery coming with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in ſight of the Walls, fire divers pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Cannon, and were anſwered in the ſame language: The garriſon at the ſame time appearing with Enſigns Spread, Trumpets ſounding, and Drums beating, ſeeming thereby reſolute to make a vigorous defence, in caſe they were beſieged. Whereupon he paſſed on to expect the <hi>Tartars,</hi> who under the leading of <hi>Ingreni</hi> Kan, Son or Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phew to the Great <hi>Tartarian</hi> Cham, was upon his march into <hi>Hungary</hi> by the way of <hi>Tranſylvania;</hi> where as well of the <hi>Tranſylvanians</hi> their Friends, as thoſe that were their Enemies, they made ſpoil. Upon notice of which, and to
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:35052:41"/>prevent ſuch a conjunction, Major-General <hi>Schuts</hi> poſted himſelf near <hi>Tranſchin,</hi> who there in conjunction with the Prince <hi>Lubomirski,</hi> made a body of 12000 Horſe and Foot, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecting daily a reinforcement from <hi>Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burg;</hi> whither the Troops from all parts were drawing, to recruit as occaſion required it. The Imperial Army, the groſs of whoſe Body lay incamped at <hi>Commora,</hi> from whence a conſiderable Party was ſent out by the Dukes com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, under the leading of Collonel <hi>Monthazon,</hi> to burn the Bridg on the River <hi>Grann,</hi> over which the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Army was to march, in order to their advancing towards <hi>Newheuſel:</hi> But ere their arrival, the <hi>Turks</hi> had ſtrongly poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed it with a detached Party, ſent out by the Baſſa of <hi>Buda,</hi> who about a League from thence, was incamped for the ſecurity of <hi>Gran;</hi> into which he had put 2000 Foot and 1000 Horſe, 1000 of the former being Janizaries, ſo that they could not effect their deſign.</p>
            <p>During theſe tranſactions, the <hi>Czar</hi> of <hi>Moſcovy,</hi> by his Ambaſſador, had often
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:35052:41"/>conferences with the Miniſters of <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> in order to his entring into the League agreed upon between <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, offering <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>; but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> that he had or could this Summer have any conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Forces in the Field, it came at this time to no concluſion, though the Treaty continued, and ſtill continues on Foot; that Prince being greatly deſirous to regain the Towns which the <hi>Tartars,</hi> ſecretly encouraged thereto by the <hi>Turks,</hi> took from the <hi>Moſcovian</hi> Dukedome, during the inteſtine broils, and clan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtine Revolutions of that Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; in which the Great Duke fell by Poiſon, and moſt of the Nobility by the hands of the rude Multitude, who under pretence of revenging their Princes death, committed all manner of outrages, laying Houſes waſt with Fire, plundering, murthering, raviſhing of Women, deflowering Virgins, ſeizing upon the Goods of Merchants, over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwing Temples, and all other wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs; for ſuch was, is, and will be, the miſerable condition of thoſe King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:35052:42"/>or States, where the rude multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude turn Reformers, and pretend to do juſtice upon offenders. But to return.</p>
            <p>By this time, the Electoral Princes being ſenſible how much the great Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my of the <hi>Turks</hi> conduced to the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement of the Rebels, and that if preparations were not ſpeedily made, the Imperial Army under the command of the Duke of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> would prove too weak to keep the Field againſt ſuch a multitude, uſed great diligence in rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing freſh Troops. Nor were there Volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiers of divers Nations wanting to flock to the Imperial Camp, as deſirous of nothing more than to fight againſt the common Enemy, who appeared ſo formidable to Chriſtendom, ſo that ſix new Regiments were compleated, four of which were commanded to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue at <hi>Presburg</hi> till they had orders to march further; and the other two kept on their way to the Army, encamped between <hi>Commora</hi> and <hi>Newheuſel:</hi> who in their way encountred 500 <hi>Turks,</hi> that were advanced as far as <hi>Newſtadt,</hi> when between the fore-runners of the
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:35052:42"/>Imperialiſts and the ſaid <hi>Turks,</hi> there happened a ſharp encounter: for the <hi>Turks</hi> ſuppoſing the Imperialiſts inferior to them in number, by reaſon the Hills interpoſed between the advanced, and thoſe that were yet to advance, and loth to loſe the Booty they had got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, which conſiſted of much Cattle; they came reſolutely to the encounter, firing with their Harquebuſſes thrice round; when as the Vaunt-guard of the Imperialiſts anſwered them with the like ſalutes, whoſe Rear-guard perceiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them ingaged, drew off, and paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the Hill, appeared at the back of the <hi>Turks</hi> drawn up in Battalia, which they no ſooner perceived, but deſpairing to prevail, as alſo of any ſuccour, they being advanced ten Leagues from their body, they threw down their Arms for the moſt part, and betook themſelves to flight, in which, and upon the place, 200 were killed, and the reſt, or, at leaſtways, the greateſt part of them, fell into the hands of the Imperial Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, ſent out from the Camp near <hi>Commora,</hi> to obſerve the motion of the Enemy near <hi>Gran.</hi> The Booty reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:35052:43"/>was 300 head of Cattle, 67 Slaves and much Houſhold-ſtuff, which they had taken from the Villagers by the way as they had paſſed: amongſt them was taken priſoner a Nephew to the Baſſa of <hi>Buda;</hi> who upon ſtrict exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation confeſſed, that the <hi>Grand Signior</hi>'s Army conſiſted of the chiefeſt ſtrength of <hi>Aſia</hi> and <hi>Gracia,</hi> and that by the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of <hi>Auguſt</hi> they reckoned (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counting the <hi>Tartars</hi> that were coming to their aid, and thoſe to be ſent by the Princes of <hi>Tranſylvania, Moldavia,</hi> and <hi>Vallachia,)</hi> to have in the Field in <hi>Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gary</hi> 300000 effectual men, with part of which it was reſolved to fight the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perial Army, if it could be drawn to a Battle, whilſt another part beſieged <hi>Raab, Commora,</hi> and other Imperial For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treſſes, the <hi>Grand Signior</hi> not doubting but to make him Maſter of the remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing part of <hi>Hungary</hi> and <hi>Auſtria,</hi> having ſworn by the ſacred Head (as he term<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it) of <hi>Mahomet,</hi> not to withdraw his Army, till he had poſſeſſed himſelf of <hi>Vienna.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This advice, ſome ſuppoſed too Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mantick, only to curry favour for his
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:35052:43"/>better treatment, and that by receiving more liberty than ordinary, he might make his eſcape: For he moreover added, That he did not greatly favour the Mahumetan Superſtition, but was greatly deſirous to become a Chriſtian, yet was he ſent priſoner to <hi>Raab,</hi> there to remain till further orders.</p>
            <p>The menaces of the <hi>Grand Signior,</hi> though indeed he had a powerful Army on foot, and every day expected to be in thoſe parts; had not ſuch effects upon the Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> nor the Council of War, that daily aſſembled in the Camp, as to make them think of with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawing the Leaguer from before <hi>New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heuſel:</hi> but the rather induced them to preſs the ſiege with greater reſolution and vigor, that ſo if it were poſſible to be Maſters of that important place, (which ſo few years ſince coſt the <hi>Turks</hi> 30000 Lives to obtain it) before the groſs of the <hi>Turks</hi> Army could paſs the River <hi>Gran,</hi> in order to attempt its re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief, or the <hi>Tartars</hi> joyn with Count <hi>Teckely,</hi> to fall into <hi>Sileſia.</hi> This impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant place is ſcituate in a fair plain, on the further bank of the River <hi>Neytra,</hi>
               <pb n="72" facs="tcp:35052:44"/>encompaſſed with a Mote and deep Trenches, Palizadoes, and divers Flan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers; the Battlements of the Walls, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing intermixed with ſmall Towers or Bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warks for playing the Cannon on, or playing with Small-Shot, in caſe of a Storm, for there they ſtand ſecure from the force of the Leaguerers Small-Shot, and advantagiouſly from all ſides annoy them to the Land ſide: For the River making a Point or Bend, as it were, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloſes two parts. There ſtands a ſtrong Caſtle, though not appearing more than twenty Cubits above on the Platform or Battlements, on which are uſually planted thirty pieces of great Ord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance.</p>
            <p>To encounter this danger, the Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rialiſts having raiſed two Batteries, play ſo furiouſly, that with their Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non they diſmounted divers Pieces of the Enemies; many of which were broken with the violence of the Shot from another Battery, that from four Mortars threw in about twenty Grana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>does in one day; which killed about 100 of the Beſieged, and demoliſhed a conſiderable number of Houſes, and
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:35052:44"/>amongſt other things, beat down the Turret of their chief Mosk or Temple: and that the Garriſon was in great con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſternation, it was reported by a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Slave, who made his eſcape over the Wall, and fled to the Imperialiſts: adding, That the Inhabitants having their Houſes demoliſhed in great num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber by the Shot of Cannon, Bombs and Granadoes; did greatly murmur againſt the Governour, ſaying, That the Grand Viſier neglected and delay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed their relief, and that it was but rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon they ſhould provide for their own ſafeties in time, by capitulating with the Beſiegers; who if things came to extremity, if they ſpared their lives which was doubtful whether they would or not, would certainly plunder them, and ſtrip them out of all they had: and that this diſcontent of the common people, the Governour had uſed great diligence to quiet and calm, by many perſwaſions, putting them in hopes of the Viſiers and Aga of the Janizaries approach with 50000 Foot and 30000 Horſe, and that a greater power would follow from <hi>Belgrade,</hi> and that upon their paſſing
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:35052:45"/>the River <hi>Gran,</hi> the Viſier of <hi>Buda</hi> would joyn them with 20000 more, who were poſted under his command upon an eminence near <hi>Gran</hi> Town: But ſome of the moſt turbulent ſeeming ſtill diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſatisfied, he cauſed ſix to be hanged up for a terrour to the reſt, and to deter them from mutinying, which upon the Imperialiſts preſſing the Siege they were prone to, and immediately commanded the Captains to prepare for a Sally, and eſpecially thoſe that were lodged on the Counterſcap. Which on the tenth of <hi>June</hi> they did, advancing under ſhelter of the Night as far as the <hi>Baſtion-trench;</hi> but being furiouſly charged by the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perialiſts, they were beaten into the Town with great loſs; in which action the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perialiſts loſt 33 men, and amongſt them three Officers of note, but the <hi>Turks</hi> trible the number: for being puſhed on by their Commanders, who ſeldom ſpare their men, they fell unawares in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a fortified work, where were lodged ſix Companies of <hi>Croats,</hi> who with their broad Swords cut in pieces all that entered.</p>
            <pb n="75" facs="tcp:35052:45"/>
            <p>Whilſt this was doing, a Bombe fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in the Town; fired one of their Store-houſes, which inraged by the Wind, drove on, conſuming as near as could be computed by the continuance of the flame, twenty Houſes, giving light alſo to the Action: For during the conflagration, all the Outworks were enlightened ſo far, as to ſee each particular, though this happened between one and two in the Morning.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Turks</hi> beaten into the Town, the better to prevent Supplies of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion being brought up the River, or any Forces that by Night might enter the Garriſon, (for it was more than ſuſpected that the Baſſa of <hi>Buda</hi> had ſuch a deſign) The Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded the Regiments of <hi>Halleweil, Ladrow, Khery</hi> and <hi>Caſtelli</hi> to reinforce the Body of Men under the command of the Palatine of <hi>Hungary,</hi> with which he had poſted himſelf on the other ſide the <hi>Neytra.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The news of the Siege of <hi>Newheuſel,</hi> and the ſucceſs of the Imperialiſts in advancing and carrying it on, being come to the Ears of the Prime Viſier,
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:35052:46"/>and that the <hi>Polonian</hi> King was advancing with a ſtrong power, intending to paſs the River <hi>Olſe</hi> at <hi>Jublow, Row,</hi> or <hi>Telſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chen,</hi> in order to his paſſing into <hi>Hunga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry:</hi> He ſent a conſiderable ſupply of Mony to the Baſſa of <hi>Caminietz,</hi> to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able him to raiſe a body of <hi>Coſſacks,</hi> to be commanded in chief by the Cham of <hi>Tartary,</hi> to obſerve the motions, and oppoſe the proceedings of the <hi>Poles.</hi> Theſe people called <hi>Coſſacks</hi> were once united to the Kingdom of <hi>Polonia,</hi> and ſerved them upon all occaſions, yet choſe Captains of their own, and did not acknowledg any King; yet proved exceeding ſerviceable, eſpecially to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent the incurſions of the <hi>Tartars</hi> into <hi>Lithuania, Podolia,</hi> and other Provinces of the <hi>Poles,</hi> into which they made frequent inroads, as living for the moſt part upon ſpoil. When in the Reign of <hi>Vldiſlayus,</hi> they ſeparated themſelves, for that the ſaid King warred upon them, either to bring them under his ſubjecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or utterly to extirpate them; but his project took not, for chooſing them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves Captains of divers Nations, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing indeed a medley of people, they
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:35052:46"/>joyn'd with their brethren the <hi>Moſcovite Coſſacks,</hi> and fought divers dreadful Battles with the <hi>Polonians</hi> with various ſucceſs; till at length being wearied, they paſt the <hi>Iſter</hi> and <hi>Boriſthenus,</hi> and there had Lands aſſigned them by the <hi>Turk</hi> and <hi>Moſcovite,</hi> they well know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thoſe men to be the Shield of <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi> There they continued, having divers conflicts with the <hi>Tartars</hi> and <hi>Poles</hi> till the death of <hi>Vldiſlayus</hi> and ſome years after: When as the <hi>Poles</hi> perceiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing themſelves for want of their guard upon the Frontiers, lye open and expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to the fury of the ſavage <hi>Tartars;</hi> who like ſo many ravenous wild beaſts, made frequent inrodes, and with fire and Sword waſted the fruitfulleſt part of the Countrey, driving away herds of Cattle, and carrying Men, Women and Children into miſerable captivity. It was in the Dyet at <hi>Leopol</hi> agreed, That Deputies ſhould be ſent to the <hi>Coſſacks,</hi> to invite them in the name of the Eſtates of <hi>Poland,</hi> to return to their antient Habitations: Which ſome of them did, but others being ſettled with their Families refuſed it: ſo that
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:35052:47"/>at this day they indifferently ſerve the <hi>Turks</hi> or Chriſtians in their Wars, liv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for the moſt part by the Sword, being always ready to eſpouſe the quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel of him that will bid moſt, be it right or wrong.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Turks</hi> Army by this time being upon its march, and the beſieged in <hi>Newheuſel</hi> continuing to make a vigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous defence, continually repairing by Night what the Cannon beat down off the Walls in the Day; and that in the opinion of the Engineers, they could not run their Mines to the Wall, by ſuch means to become maſters of the place in leſs than a Fortnight: A Council was held in the Camp, in order to come to a reſult, Whether the ſiege ſhould be raiſed or continued? On one hand it was urged, That the ſuddain raiſing the Siege would imply a fear in the Imperialiſts, and prove advantagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to the <hi>Turks,</hi> and heighten their courage, and redound to the diſhonour of the Empire; and that in conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion thereof it was rather convenient to hazzard a battle with the advanced part of the <hi>Turks</hi> Army, that was ſent to
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:35052:47"/>relieve the Beſieged: or give a furious aſſault to the Town on all parts, in which it might probably fall out, that they ſhould carry it by ſtorm. But theſe Councils were on the other hand not thought convenient at ſuch a juncture, it being alledged, That the Army was not yet compleat, and that in unadviſedly hazzarding a Battle without the conjunction of all the For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, or at leaſt thoſe the King of <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> was bringing into the Field, was to hazzard at one Caſt all the hereditary Countries of the Empire. As for at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempting the place by Storm, experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence had already made it apparent, that it was a matter of great difficulty, and more men muſt neceſſarily be loſt than the place was worth; That it was no policy (if the attempt ſhould prove ſucceſsful, as it was greatly to be queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned whether it would or not) to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe a Town at the price of ſo much blood. But ſomething muſt be reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved before the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Forces advanced ſo near as either to oblige the Army to Battle, or a diſhonourable Retreat. The Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> was of the former opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:35052:48"/>being deſirous of nothing more than to give the Infidels Battle, if it was poſſible to oblige them thereto. But whilſt theſe debates were undeter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined, the Emperor being ſenſible of the ſtate of affairs, and not willing to hazzard the ſtrength of his Empire at a Caſt, ſent an expreſs order from <hi>Vienna</hi> to the Duke, to quit the ſiege, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn to his former Camp near <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mora:</hi> which he accordingly did. And immediately after his departure, the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieged ſallied out, and ſet their Pioneers on work to fill up the Trenches, and demoliſh the battery the Imperialiſts had raiſed, for fear that they upon ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond thought, or a new reinforcement, might return to the Siege.</p>
            <p>In this enterprize the Imperialiſts made four attacks upon the Counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcarps, Half-Moon and Ravelin; in which, and at the ſeven ſallies the <hi>Turks</hi> made, they loſt 500 men: And the <hi>Turks</hi> are ſuppoſed to loſe double the number, 100 at once being killed and ſpoiled in a Bulwark, which was blown up by a Granado, containing fifty pound of Powder.</p>
            <pb n="81" facs="tcp:35052:48"/>
            <p>Whilſt <hi>Newheuſel</hi> was beſieged, the Palatine of <hi>Hungary</hi> taking the advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take of the <hi>Turks</hi> conſternation, drew out a detatchment of 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>00 Foot, and 500 Horſe, and marching croſs the Countrey, laid ſiege to the Fortreſs of <hi>Scarone,</hi> ſummoning it to ſurrender; but the Governour refuſing, he from a ſmall riſing battered it with four Demi-Culverings for the ſpace of ſix Hours, in which time he laid open a breach ſo wide that ſix might march abreaſt: which the beſieged perceiving, ſounded a Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, but could get no other Conditions than to be made Priſoners of War, the whole Garriſon not conſiſting of more than 68 <hi>Turks,</hi> of which eight were killed with the Cannon-ſhot, and the remainder carried Priſoners to <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vigrade.</hi> After which, the Palatine hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing put 150 men into the place, and furniſhed them with all things neceſſary, returned to his Poſt; where he had notice, that the Count <hi>Palſi</hi> had joyned the Imperial Army with 3000 of the new Levies.</p>
            <pb n="82" facs="tcp:35052:49"/>
            <p>Count <hi>Teckely</hi> being all this while bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſy in the upper <hi>Hungary,</hi> to get himſelf effectually acknowledged Prince of that Province, and finding cold returns of ſuch meſſages as he ſent to divers of the Nobility upon that occaſion, and eſpecially of the Governours of the <hi>Berg Towns,</hi> whom he preſſed more than any other: He reſolved to compel them by Force to do what by words he could not oblige them to, and thereupon ſent a Body of 3000 <hi>Hungarians,</hi> and 1000 <hi>Tartarian</hi> Light-Horſe-men, in his name, to take poſſeſſion of thoſe Towns; as likewiſe to poſſeſs the Silver Mines, not far diſtant from them. Not ſo ſeeming ſatisfied, as well knowing the <hi>Turks</hi> were at hand to back him, he ſent forth his Summons to injoyn the Inhabitants of the Counties of <hi>Neutra, Trenchin</hi> and <hi>Taroz,</hi> to ſupply him with Proyiſion for the ſubſiſtence of his Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my; threatning upon failure thereof to plunder and burn their Towns; which forc'd divers of the Countrey people, and ſuch as lived in places ſubject to the incurſions of the Rebels, to remove with their ſubſtance into Towns of
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:35052:49"/>ſtrength: by reaſon at the ſame time, the Governours of the Fortreſſes had ſent an Expreſs, under pain of being treated as enemies to the Empire. So that between both, the wretched peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple were in great perplexity: but upon certain notice, That the <hi>Turks</hi> Army conſiſting of 80000 Horſe and Foot were marching with all ſpeed into thoſe parts; a great number of Villages have complyed to <hi>Teckely</hi>'s demands, and amongſt other, <hi>Papa, Veſprin,</hi> and <hi>Totis,</hi> have put themſelves under his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection.</p>
            <p>The Duke of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> upon his quit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the ſiege of <hi>Newheuſel,</hi> having no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice, That the Baſſa of <hi>Buda</hi> had a deſign to fall into <hi>Moravia</hi> and <hi>Sileſia</hi> with the body of men under his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, and for that intent was upon his march; he with the Imperial Army In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>camped upon the bank of the <hi>Danube</hi> to hinder his paſſage, as likewiſe to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure the conveyance of Proviſion to the Imperial Garriſons ſcituate upon the banks of that River, and to prevent any deſign the <hi>Turks</hi> might have upon the Iſle of <hi>Schutz.</hi> And at the ſame time
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:35052:50"/>the Palatine of <hi>Hungary</hi> is poſted on the <hi>Waag</hi> near <hi>Trenchin,</hi> daily expecting the King of <hi>Poland,</hi> who with his Forces lay at that time incamped near <hi>Cracaw;</hi> as alſo orders from the Emperor how to proceed in the juncture of affairs, which he received upon the return of the Duke of <hi>Saxe Lewenburg,</hi> who was ſent to <hi>Vienna</hi> to give his Imperial Majeſty an account of the State of affairs; and whilſt he lay incamped on the <hi>Danube,</hi> he cauſed the Fortifications of <hi>Raab</hi> to be repaired, putting a reinforcement in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it, and furniſhing it with all things ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to hold a long ſiege, and make a reſolute defence, in caſe it ſhould be beſieged.</p>
            <p>And now great was the expectation of all men; for the Viſier with his Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, having paſſed divers ſmall Rivers, by Plaſhing of Trees, or bridging them over with Boats, by ſwift marches ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced as far as <hi>Stat Weiſſemberg,</hi> within ſix hours march of the Imperial Camp; his Forces, Horſe and Foot, conſiſting of 80000 effectual men. And thither he ſent for Count <hi>Teckely,</hi> who immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly went to attend him: When to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:35052:50"/>the Fortifications on the <hi>Neytra</hi> from falling into the <hi>Turks</hi> hands, the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror ſent orders to Count <hi>Chackey,</hi> who commands on that ſide, to demoliſh them: Which was accordingly perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. And now ſo near were the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches of the two Armies, that divers Skirmiſhes with various ſucceſs hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened between parties. The <hi>Turks</hi> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patiently expecting 12000 <hi>Tartars,</hi> who were upon their march through <hi>Molda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>via,</hi> to joyn them. And the Imperia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſts, as earneſtly expected the Prince of <hi>Tranſylvania;</hi> (who envying Count <hi>Teck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley</hi>'s advancement, and miſtruſting the Grand Signior has a deſign to deprive him of his Principality) promiſed, as the rumour went, to take the Field with 18 or 20000 men, at arrival of the <hi>Polonian</hi> Forces, and to act offenſively againſt the <hi>Turks.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>On the 2 of <hi>July</hi> 1683. the Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> having received advice, That a Body of <hi>Turks</hi> and <hi>Tartars</hi> had paſſed the <hi>Raab</hi> at <hi>Segine,</hi> and exerciſed all manner of cruelties upon the people where they came, burning their Houſes, deflowring their Daughters, raviſhing
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:35052:51"/>and ripping up their Wives daſhing their young Children againſt the P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ment and haling ſuch as were of ability of bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy into miſerable bondage, with a thouſand the like cruelties, and beſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities: He detached a conſiderable party to oppoſe their further proceedings, and oblige them to repaſs the River; which they accordingly did, and after that, having made a ſhew, as if they intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to lay ſiege either to <hi>Leopolſtadt</hi> or <hi>Raab:</hi> The Imperial Horſe poſted them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves near <hi>Altenburg,</hi> and the Foot in the Iſle of <hi>Schutz,</hi> to be in a readineſs as occaſion ſhould ſerve to aſſiſt either of the places. But this ſtratagem being in a ſhort time diſcovered, and that the <hi>Turks</hi> real intentions were to get be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Horſe and Foot, to hinder their acting joyntly: The Imperial Horſe ſent their Baggage towards <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenburg;</hi> which the <hi>Turks</hi> attacked with 3000 men, but being fought withal, and for a long time couragiouſly repulſed by the Convoy, which exceeded not 600 Horſe, they retired, leaving 100 of their men dead upon the place: But in their retreat meeting a party of 800
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:35052:51"/>
               <hi>Turks,</hi> they again rallied, Whereupon the Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> from the main Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, made what ſpeed he could with 4000 Light-Horſe, inſomuch that there happened a ſharp and obſtinate Skirmiſh between both parties; in which the Imperialiſts loſt 1200 men, and all their baggage, valued at 40000 Guilders. The <hi>Turks</hi> are ſaid to have loſt in this skirmiſh 1700 men, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them divers of note. The Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> was ingaged in the midſt of the Enemies, and near unto him were wounded, the Prince of <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voy,</hi> General <hi>Rubatta,</hi> and the Count <hi>d' Lamberg,</hi> and the Prince of <hi>Aremberg:</hi> The Princes of <hi>Savoy</hi> and <hi>Aremberg</hi> ſoon after dying of their wounds. After which the Imperial Horſe making good the retreat, paſſed the Bridge, and joyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Foot, who during the Action, being divided by the River, could not come to their aſſiſtance.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Turks</hi> heightned by this ſucceſs, and being recruited by 8000 more of their accomplices, laid ſiege to <hi>Raah,</hi> from whoſe Walls the Guns played up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them ſo furiouſly, that they perceiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:35052:52"/>that ſiege too hot for them, they after having burnt an adjacent Village called <hi>Petronello,</hi> quitted it, and march<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing outwards joyned the groſs body of the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Army, under the leading of the Grand Viſier, who marched directly towards <hi>Vienna,</hi> the chief City of <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtria,</hi> and Bulwark of the Empire, ſpoil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and ravaging the Countrey after ſo dreadful a manner, that the Inhabitants fled before them, with ſuch things as were portable, like droves of Sheep; and divers Towns to avoid ſuch cruel treat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, put themſelves under their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection, the Countrey all about them being in a flame. There might one be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the helliſh <hi>Tartars,</hi> like ſo many fiends, dragging and haling the Chriſtians faſt bound in Ropes; and the barbarous <hi>Turks</hi> carrying the Heads of ſuch as they had ſlain in triumph, as it were, upon the points of their Lances, ſtill blaſpheem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Redeemer of the World, and threatning deſtruction to all Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom. Whilſt before the torrent, the Imperial Army retired under the Walls of <hi>Vienna,</hi> into which City to get en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance, the Count <hi>Staremburg,</hi> Governour
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:35052:52"/>thereof, was obliged with much brave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to fight his way through the Enemy, with a Body of Foot, with which he had been abroad to obſerve their moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: and immediately entring, gave orders for firing the Suburbs, and pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing the Guns upon the Wall, reſolving to make a reſolute and brave de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence.</p>
            <p>Whilſt the tranſaction happened, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jor General <hi>Schutz</hi> had better ſucceſs, for upon notice that a ſtrong party of the Rebels were about to paſs the <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nube</hi> about ſix Leagues from his Poſt, he drew off, and marched immediately to impede their paſſage: And finding them making proviſion for their tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portation, he fell upon them with ſuch courage and bravery, that after a hot diſpute, he put them to the rout, kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling 200 upon the place, taking 106 Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoners, with ſeven Enſigns, and a great Booty, which they had gotten in their Progreſs. Their intent-was to have fallen into <hi>Sileſia,</hi> there to expect a body of <hi>Tartars,</hi> who were on their march to joyn them.</p>
            <pb n="90" facs="tcp:35052:53"/>
            <p>The <hi>Turks</hi> Camp increaſing before <hi>Vienna,</hi> and furiouſly preſſing the ſiege, though the beſieged made a brave and reſolute defence: Yet knowing they could not ſubſiſt without relief from abroad, the Biſhop of <hi>Aichſtadt,</hi> the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perial Commiſſioner, by a Memorial re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſents unto the Diet for that purpoſe aſſembled, the imminent danger wherein the City was; as likewiſe the whole Circle of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> which muſt of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity fall into the hands of the unmer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciful Infidels, if a ſpeedy courſe were not taken to relieve it; and under what mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries the Countries about the beſieged City groaned, they were not igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant: Therefore in the name of his Imperial Majeſty, he prayed them to lay aſide all other buſineſs and debates, and come to a quick reſolution about raiſing Men and Money, ſufficient to enable the Imperial Army, if not to raiſe the Siege, yet to keep the Field, and prevent the farther progreſs of the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Arms: which they promiſed to do. And immediately thereupon, the reſpective Deputies Diſpatched away Letters to their Principals, to acquaint
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:35052:53"/>them with the Reſolves of the Dyet. Whereupon the Duke of <hi>Bavaria</hi> drew his Forces together with all imaginable expedition; and as the Vaunt-guard of his Troops, diſpatched a Regiment of Foot, and another of Horſe, to joyn the Duke of <hi>Lorrain;</hi> whom they found poſted about ten Leagues on this ſide <hi>Vienna,</hi> his Camp ſtrongly fortified, and in good order; his Army conſiſting in Horſe, Foot and Dragoons, of no leſs than 35000 effectual men, with the which he intended, as ſoon as the Troops joyned him, to fight the Grand Viſier, or oblige him to draw off from before the City, and raiſe the ſiege.</p>
            <p>During theſe tranſactions, his Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial Majeſty remained at <hi>Paſſaw,</hi> ſolici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the Chriſtian Princes to draw to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether their Forces with all expedition, to oppoſe the Infidels; who with great labour and diligence advanced their Trenches, as knowing that if they linger the ſiege, the Chriſtian Forces would be upon them, and oblige them to riſe from before it: Therefore with their Batteries they fired inceſſantly, ruining a great part of the Wall near the <hi>Carin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thian</hi>
               <pb n="92" facs="tcp:35052:54"/>Gate; notwithſtanding the beſieg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed made a gallant and reſolute defence, being in want neither of Ammunition nor Proviſion: Yet that all the Countrey round about was in a conſternation inex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſible; the people through fear and amazement, flying every where through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Circle.</p>
            <p>The Rebels taking advantage of the retreat of the Imperialiſts, deſiſted not to commit many and great outrages, burning and plundering all before them; when coming near <hi>Budekim,</hi> in the upper <hi>Sileſia,</hi> the Governour of that Garriſon ſallied out upon them, and gave them a brisk incounter, but being overpowered with numbers, was obliged to retire with ſome loſs. This ſo inraged the Rebels, that they reſolved to attack that Fortreſs; and did it ſo ſuccesfully, that notwithſtanding the reſolute de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of the beſieged, they carried it at the third aſſault, putting moſt of the Garriſon to the Sword, and plundring without exception, all the Inhabitants. At which ſiege, there ran a report, that Count <hi>Teckely</hi> was mortally wounded, and ſoon after, that he was dead; though
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:35052:54"/>it proved altogether a miſtake, for he was not perſonally there, but acted by his Lieutenant. The loſs of this place, greatly alarmed the neighbouring Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſons, and obliged them to put them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in an extraordinary poſture of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence; eſpecially, upon notice that 10 thouſand <hi>Tartars</hi> were marching with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in twelve Leagues, to joyn the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels.</p>
            <p>The Grand Viſier, at the ſiege of <hi>Vienna</hi> did not at all ſpare his men, think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by ſuch reſoluteneſs to daunt the beſieged, and bring them the ſooner to a Capitulation: To come to which, he has not only by Letters ſhot in upon Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows; but by other means, as fending his Letters by captive <hi>Auſtrians,</hi> made large Promiſes, and large Threats; on the one hand, aſſuring them of Liberty, free exerciſe of Religion, and indemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of their Perſons and Eſtates: On the other, he magnified the Force, Power, and Reſolution of his Maſter, ſwearing by <hi>Mahumet,</hi> if they ſtood out to extremity, and obliged him to take it by ſtorm, which he was reſolved to do, for that no relief was to be hoped
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:35052:55"/>for on their part; he would put all to the Sword, without exception, and that the moſt obſtinate in oppoſing his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, ſhould expire by the moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite torments. But theſe threats or promiſes were too low and mean to have any effects, or make any impreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on on the minds of men of bravery and reſolution, who had devoted their lives to the defence of that City, and the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of the Emperours honour; though indeed ſome of the puſillani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Burghers, looking back upon their Wives and Children, were for yielding up the place; for which, and for muti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying upon that occaſion, as a terrour to the reſt, five or ſix of them were exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted, and an Order publiſhed, That under ſevere penalties, no man ſhould be ſo hardy, as once to name or men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion any thing tending to a Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>render.</p>
            <p>The Viſier, thus fruſtrated in his hopes and expectation, gave order to raiſe another Battery againſt the new Bulwark, from which he battered it inceſſantly for 16 hours with great fury; but in the end had moſt of his Cannon
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:35052:55"/>diſinounted by the beſieged, and a ſally made upon the Trenches; in which 300 <hi>Turks</hi> were killed, and of the Imperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aliſts fifty; amongſt whom was a Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of Horſe and an Enſign bearer: But what more conduced to the advantage of the Imperialiſts, under the favour of this action the Pioneers filled up divers of their Works, and broke into their Mines in divers places, which they diſcovered by ſounding them. The Count <hi>Staremberg</hi> Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our of the place, omitted no labour nor induſtry to defend it, giving moſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable proofs of his conduct and cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, to the great incouragement of thoſe that ſerved under him; for where-ever the Walls were moſt rent and ſhattered, and the Cannon played moſt furiouſly, there would he be, labouring at the Works ſometimes with his own hands, and at other times incouraging his Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers with words and rewards.</p>
            <p>By this time, the <hi>Turks</hi> having fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed three new Batteries, began to throw their Bombs, which ruined divers houſes; to prevent which, many of thoſe that were neareſt to the Wall,
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:35052:56"/>the Beſieged covered with Earth, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially the flat roofed ones, which moſt in that City are: which ſtrategem hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered frequently the Bombs from doing their deſired execution. When in the mean time, the <hi>German</hi> Engineers ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving from the Bulwarks levelled their Cannon againſt the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Batteries, broke and diſmounted moſt of their Cannon, ruining, and for the moſt part demoliſhing the Batteries, killing a great number of the Infidels: Inſomuch that the Viſier ſent to the Count, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand a ceſſation for ſome hours, to bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry the dead; but indeed to repair the Batteries, though it was not conjectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red that leſs than 300 ſlain lay ſcattered up and down, whoſe noyſome ſmell greatly infected the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Camp: not was the imperious <hi>Turk</hi> contented to make this demand only, but according to the wonted pride of the <hi>Ottomans,</hi> he by the ſame Meſſenger gave him a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond time to underſtand, That in caſe he did not in time ſurrender the place, but obſtinately held out, till it ſhould be taken by ſtorm, he would put Men, Women, and Children to the Sword.
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:35052:56"/>To which the Count as boldly, and ſouldier-like, returned anſwer: That his menaces might be ſpared; that for his part, he knew better how to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend the place, than ever to think of ſurrendring it, of which by his actions he would convince him; nor would he conſent to any ceſſation. This anſwer made the <hi>Turk</hi> fume and chaſe exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly, but in vain; for although he commanded all the Cannon to play in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſantly all the 1 and 22 of <hi>July,</hi> yet they did little execution; or if they did, the Citizens and others, who la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boured therein, repaired it, and where ever the fierceſt battery happened, there they countermured and raiſed Rampiers of earth to hinder the ſhaking of the Wall: Nor did he only batter, but commanded his men to give an at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tack upon the Ravelin in three places, their Officers thruſting and beating ſuch on as lagged or ſeemed unwilling to preſs forward; but in this they were altogether unſuccesful; for what by the Cannon from the Work, and the Town, and volleys of ſmall ſhot from the Palizadoes and Breſt-works, they
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:35052:57"/>were forced to retire 2000 leſs than they came on.</p>
            <p>The war remaining at this point, the Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> having received a ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply of 5000 men, the better to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage the beſieged, drew near the City, incamping with his whole Army at <hi>Krembs</hi> on the <hi>Danube</hi> about three Lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gues and a half from <hi>Vienna,</hi> within hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Cannon, and ſight of the Leaguer; and there received advice from the King of <hi>Poland,</hi> That he was upon his march with an Army of 40000 effectual men, and that by the 20 of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> he would be before <hi>Vienna,</hi> and oblige the <hi>Turks</hi> to riſe, or come to a general Battle; which advice he cauſed to be conveyed to the beſieged by a Fiſherman, who adventured to ſwim over the River; and thereby ſo incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged them, that the next morning they made another ſally upon the <hi>Turks,</hi> and finding them altogether unprepared, made a great ſlaughter, beating them out of their Trenches, and throwing down their Works; which ſo much alarmed the Camp, that the Viſier ſuſpected the Imperial Army was at hand, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:35052:57"/>immediately drew up into Battalia, commanding 1000 Janizaries, and 2000 Spahies to ſuccour the Leaguers that maintained the Works; upon whoſe arrival, the Imperialiſts returned into the City, having killed between 3 or 400 of the enemies, and taken eight Enſigns: Which negligence of duty in the <hi>Turks,</hi> the Viſier puniſhed by the death of the Zangiack, that command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in chief on part of the Works. This action was no ſooner over, but the Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> had notice by his Scouts, that a great convoy of Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and Ammunition was on its way to the <hi>Turks</hi> Camp before <hi>Vienna:</hi> He commanded out a ſtrong party to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tack it, who accordingly did; but find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>Turks</hi> that guarded it, obſtinate, and not willing to ſurrender it without blows, a ſharp diſpute happened, and continued hot for the ſpace of two hours, in which time 600 <hi>Turks</hi> being killed upon the place, the reſt fled, ſome to the Camp, and others to Count <hi>Teckely,</hi> who lyes on the frontiers of <hi>Sileſia;</hi> lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the Baggage to the Imperialiſts, who loſt 58 men in this action; but in
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:35052:58"/>the end brought their booty to the Camp, computed worth 40000 Dol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars: for it conſiſted of 1000 Waggons all well laden.</p>
            <p>The Imperial Miniſters in the name of his Imperial Majeſty, having motioned to the Count <hi>d' Crecy,</hi> the <hi>French</hi> Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, That the Troops of that Crown might not moleſt the Empire, nor any of its dependences during his Imperial Majeſties being involved in war with the <hi>Turk:</hi> The ſaid Count ſent to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint the King his Maſter with what had been propoſed; and having received Inſtruction, on that affair, He on the 26 of <hi>July</hi> preſented a memorial, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he acquainted them, That the King his Maſter would not take advantage of the condition the Empire is in, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the war with the <hi>Turks;</hi> but would make a truce with his Imperial Majeſty for the ſpace of thirty years, provided it be conſented to before the end of <hi>Auguſt:</hi> Upon which Propoſal, the Biſhop of <hi>Aichſtadt,</hi> the Imperial Miniſter, ſent to acquaint his Imperial Majeſty therewith; and to receive in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions in that affair: the Electoral
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:35052:58"/>Colledge being of opinion. That it is abſolutely neceſſary to conclude a peace with the Crown of <hi>France</hi> upon the Conditions propoſed; and that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon they ſhall be the better able to aſſiſt his Imperial Majeſty with men and money to maintain the war againſt the <hi>Turk;</hi> for that they are at preſent obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to keep Forces upon the frontiers to prevent the incurſions of the <hi>French,</hi> who are roving abroad in parties: But the reſult of this affair, at this juncture of great importance to the Empire, as yet remains undetermined and doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful.</p>
            <p>During the Treaty between the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire and Crown of <hi>France,</hi> the action grew warm at the ſiege of <hi>Vienna;</hi> for the <hi>Turks</hi> continuing their Batteries, and preſſing on the ſiege, by running their Trenches, and covering with Bavins and Planks, to defend them from the ſmall ſhot out of the Palizadoes and Flankers. The Imperialiſts on the 24 of <hi>July,</hi> made another brisk ſallie, with 3000 Foot and 2000 Horſe, who charged the <hi>Turks</hi> with ſuch fury in their Trenches, that they drove them out of
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:35052:59"/>divers works, which they had advanced near the <hi>Ravelin,</hi> and filled them up, ſetting fire to the Planks, and what elſe was combuſtible; and following their advantage, beat them to their main Works, and there diſputed it at puſh of Pike, and But-end for half an hour: du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring which ſpace, 7000 <hi>Turks</hi> advanced from the Camp to the relief of their fellows; when the Imperialiſts tired with the ſlaughter of the Infidels, of which (as ſome that were taken Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoners ſince, ſay no leſs than) 4 or 5000 periſhed in the action, they retired into the Town, carrying <hi>Turks</hi> heads upon their Lances; which they afterwards planted upon ſtakes on the Baſtions. This and the former carnages did ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect the air, that the ſmell and noy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomneſs cauſed a mortal ſickneſs in the <hi>Turks</hi> Camp, and thereby obliged the Viſier to remove with the greateſt part of his Army 3 or 4 miles diſtant from the Walls: And moreover it was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated by a Chriſtian ſlave, who in the action made his eſcape, That the <hi>Turks</hi> in running their Trenches, did happen upon a great number of dead bodies,
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:35052:59"/>full of putrefaction and contagious ſmells, who had been buried during the raging of the late Plague at <hi>Vienna;</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch, that not being able to endure the ſcent, they were often obliged to diſcontinue the work, many of them thereupon falling mortally ſick, and dying ſhortly after: So that here, as well the dead as the living contributed to the defence of the City. In the laſt ſally the Imperialiſts loſt 160 men.</p>
            <p>The Elector of <hi>Bavaria,</hi> by this time having drawn forth an Army of 13 or 14000 men, brought them to <hi>Paſſaw;</hi> where he drew them up, and exerciſed them in the preſence of the Emperor, where they for the moſt part appeared wonderful dextrous in handling their Arms, ſwift and ready in their advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and indeed expert in all military exerciſe, to the no ſmall delight of the beholders. Scarcely was this over, but News came, That General <hi>Dunwalt</hi> having notice that 7 or 8000 <hi>Tartars</hi> were fallen into the upper <hi>Auſtria,</hi> he with ſuch forces as he had under his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, and a conſiderable Band of the Peaſants, fell upon them as they were
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:35052:60"/>plundering, and ſo conſequently divided, and not in any reaſonable poſture of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, and aſter ſome diſpute, put a great number of them to the Sword, took divers of them priſoners, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered 2000 poor Chriſtian Captives, which they were dragging after them in chains, as likewiſe recovered a conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable Booty, part of which he deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered to the owners, and the reſt he di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtributed amongſt his Souldiers.</p>
            <p>Theſe ſucceſſes of the Imperialiſts, as they greatly diſmayed the <hi>Turks</hi> and Rebels, ſo they animated the Imperia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſts, and the Princes of the Circles, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing them to haſten out their Troops, inſomuch, that in a Conference held at <hi>Hasford</hi> the 27 of <hi>July,</hi> between the Biſhop of <hi>Bamberg</hi> and <hi>Wirtsbourg,</hi> and the Deputies of the Elector of <hi>Branden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burg,</hi> the Princes of <hi>Hanſpach, Bareith,</hi> &amp;c. it was reſolved, That the Troops of <hi>Franconia</hi> deſigned for the aſſiſtance of the Emperour ſhould begin their march on the 2 of <hi>Auguſt;</hi> it being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditioned, That the Biſhop and Chapter of <hi>Wirtsbourg,</hi> ſhould for this ſervice furniſh out two Regiments of Foot, and
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:35052:60"/>four Companies of Guards; and the Elector of <hi>Brandenburg,</hi> not reckoning his Quota, ſhould aſſiſt the Emperour with a body of men under the command of the Velt Marſhal <hi>Borfling:</hi> All which were immediately to be raiſed and ſent to the Imperial camp, incamped be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween <hi>Krembs</hi> and <hi>Vienna,</hi> impatiently expecting thoſe Auxiliary Troops. But from hence let us again return to the Siege of <hi>Vienna.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Turks</hi> ſtill preſſing the ſiege in hopes to carry the Town by Storm, or oblige the beſieged to ſurrender upon reaſonable propoſals, raiſed divers new Batteries in the ſtead of thoſe the beſieg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed's Cannon had ruined: Which Batte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries they chiefly manage by Renegadoes of all Nations, to whom they give dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble pay. They on the 30 of <hi>July</hi> made three attacks near <hi>Scotenburg</hi>-Gate and the <hi>Red Tower,</hi> in which they were bravely repulſed by the beſieged, who came to handy blows with them with great reſolution; whilſt the Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non from the Flankers cut off the <hi>Turks</hi> in great numbers, and ſpared not to kill ſome of the Imperialiſts, who were
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:35052:61"/>mixed, and fighting with the enemy. In theſe three attacks the <hi>Turks</hi> loſt near 8000 men: Whereupon, the Grand Viſier ſent to demand a Ceſſation to fetch off the ſlain and wounded; but Count <hi>Staremberg</hi> returned anſwer, That he had no need of Truce, his Garriſon being all in good order. The <hi>Turks</hi> ſcarce had time to breath, before the Imperialiſts making another ſally, entred the Suburb called <hi>Leopolſtadt;</hi> ſome time ſince poſſeſſed by the <hi>Turks;</hi> they beat them out, and put a conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable number of men into it to defend it, it ſerving as a Flanker to the Town, and playing furiouſly againſt the Batte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry the <hi>Turks</hi> had raiſed againſt the <hi>Scotch</hi>-Gate, diſmounting all the Cannon, and ruining the Battery, though not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out loſs on their own part, the moſt ſtout and reſolute Souldiers ſtill keeping the Walls; the Garriſon conſiſting of 18000 fighting men, beſides a great number of the Burghers, Scholars and religious perſons of all Orders, who up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on occaſion are aſſiſting. Nor is any thing of Ammunition or Proviſion want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, but a plenty ſufficient for ſeveral
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:35052:61"/>Months, according to the computation of thoſe that by the Count's order took a narrow ſurvey of the Magazines: Money being the thing moſt wanting, the Governour borrowed a conſiderable ſumm of the Religious Orders, promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to reſtore it with addition, if the City eſcape falling into the hands of the enemy; and if it ſhould ſo happen, yet to make reparation, if his life and liberty were preſerved; the which mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney he freely and cheerfully at divers times diſtributed amongſt his Souldiers: As likewiſe was ſo exact as to ſee the Proviſion fairly divided, that one has not more than another; thereby to prevent murmurs, animoſities and mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinies: Cauſing the whole Garriſon, as well Burghers as Souldiers, to take an Oath, To defend the place to the laſt extremity, and never to hearken to any propoſals or overtures from the enemy, how advantagious ſoever they may be. Theſe reſolutions, equity and bravery in the Governour, contributed not a little to the reſolution and courage of the Souldiers and Citizens, the very Women appearing every where coura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious,
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:35052:62"/>heartning and exciting their Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands to maintain and defend the City againſt the common Enemy without wearineſs or fainting. This great City, when the <hi>Turks</hi> firſt ſat down before it, had no more than 15 or 1600 men in it, and not greatly provided with Ammu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition and other neceſſaries; but as Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence had ordered it, juſt as it was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſted, <hi>viz.</hi> on the 14 of <hi>July,</hi> four great Veſſels came up the River laden with all manner of Neceſſaries, and within ſight of the enemy, recovered the Port: Though few expected the day before, that the <hi>Turks</hi> would have attempted a ſiege, in which they have always been unfortunate. For before this very City, much weaker than at preſent, <hi>Solyman</hi> the Magnificent loſt 80000, or as ſome ſay, 100000 men; and after all that he could do, being there in perſon, he was obliged to raiſe his ſiege with ſhame and diſgrace. The Duke of <hi>Lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rain</hi> likewiſe had the good luck to thruſt in 13000 Foot, and 1000 Horſe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides which upon occaſion, the Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants can make 20000 fighting men; and happy was it for the City, that the
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:35052:62"/>Garriſon and Proviſion ſo luckily en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered: for the next day the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my ſo cloſely inveſted it, that it was a work of great difficulty for a ſingle per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to get in or out.</p>
            <p>The Country round about <hi>Vienna</hi> is deſtroyed and laid waft: for upon the <hi>Turks</hi> firſt arrival, from the Walls and Towers of the City, might be ſeen 40 Villages in a flame at once; and daily for a week together, were brought into the Camp, droves of ſuch miſerable Chriſtians as the Barbarians had ſurpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed or taken in the Caſtles and ſmall Fortreſſes adjacent, which were not capable of ſtanding out, but to ſave their lives ſurrendered; though they had better have dyed like Souldiers and men of courage, than fallen into the hands of ſo barbarous an enemy, from whom they can expect nothing but ſlavery: ſo that great are the cryes and wailing of Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men and Children; which when the Wind ſat on the back of the Camp, could be diſtinctly heard by the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieged.</p>
            <p>The King of <hi>Poland</hi> having left <hi>Cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caw,</hi> with the Army under his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand,
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:35052:63"/>marched with all dilligence to joyn the Imperial Army, and in joynt confederacy to relieve the beſieged City, or to give the enemy battle. When in the mean while, the Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> having advice, that Count <hi>Teckely</hi> march<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed towards <hi>Presburg</hi> with a ſtrong pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of the <hi>Hungarian</hi> Rebels and <hi>Turks,</hi> the latter being ſent him by the Baſſa of <hi>Buda;</hi> and taking the advantage of the juncture of affairs, he intended to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiege it: He detached a ſtrong party of Horſe and Foot, and marched towards them with a reſolution to give them battle; which <hi>Teckely</hi> little ſuſpected, by reaſon the day before he had receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed advice, that he durſt not come forth of his Camp, for fear of the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, but too late finding his intelligence falſe, and that the Duke from the Walls of <hi>Presburg</hi> advanced towards him, he with his whole body of <hi>Turks</hi> and <hi>Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garians,</hi> conſiſting of 25000 men, retired in the beſt order the ſmall time would permit; but not ſo ſwift<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly but that the Imperialiſts fell in with his Rear, making of them great ſlaughter, cutting off about 6
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:35052:63"/>or 700 of them, and ſeizing upon moſt of their Baggage, Ammunition and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion, taking in all 1000 Waggons: After which the Duke reinforced the Garriſon, cauſing all the Boats that <hi>Teckely</hi> had brought thither, to bridge over the <hi>Danube,</hi> to be burnt; ſending after him the Prince <hi>Lubomirskie,</hi> with the <hi>Poliſh</hi> Horſe under his command; who for the ſpace of eight miles, had the execution of the Rear-guard, which made a kind of a running fight, the Duke with the whole Army following cloſe after. In this action the Imperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aliſts and <hi>Poles</hi> loſt 100 men, and the enemy 1500. After which, Count <hi>Teckely</hi> in great confuſion repaſſed the <hi>Waag,</hi> and the <hi>Turks</hi> ſeparating from him, returned to <hi>Newbeuſel,</hi> out of which Garriſon moſt of them were drawn. The Duke ſtay'd upon the bank of the River <hi>Marck,</hi> two miles from <hi>Presburg,</hi> to have notice of their moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as fearing they might wheel about and fall into <hi>Moravia;</hi> ſending after them General <hi>Dunwald</hi> with 1000 Light-Horſe, continually to give him an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of what he could learn in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:35052:64"/>to their inclination to action; and ſo riſing with the part of the Army he had brought, he returned to his Camp near <hi>Krembs,</hi> upon the <hi>Danube,</hi> there to expect the Elector of <hi>Bavaria</hi> and the King of <hi>Poland,</hi> both which were near at hand, with a reſolution to joyn him; theſe two Princes marching in perſon at the head of their Armies, both which Armies amount to 45000 fighting men, the flower of thoſe Countrys. Upon whoſe approach, the Grand Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſier ſent orders to the Baſſa of <hi>Buda,</hi> to draw up a body of 2000 men, out of the neighbouring Garriſons, and diſpatch them immediately to the Army, as likewiſe Ammunition and Proviſion with all ſpeed; the Army, by reaſon of the late Convoys falling into the hands of the Imperialiſts, being much diſtreſſed for want of Proviſion: He likewiſe diſpatched a Chiaus to the Grand Signior, to give him a relation of what had happened ſince the ſiege; wherein, as ſome fugitives report, he gave the Chians a ſtrict command, to aſſure him, that he would ſuddenly ſend him the Keys of <hi>Vienna:</hi> And as ſoon as
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:35052:64"/>he was departed, that he might inform the Grand Signior he left the Camp in action, he furiouſly battered, the <hi>Red Tower,</hi> thundring inceſſantly againſt it with 12 pieces of Cannon and Culver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing flinging Bullets of 52 and 58 pound weight; yet through the vigilance of the Defendants, did ſmall damage be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides renting the Battlements and Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of the Wall.</p>
            <p>The Viceroy of <hi>Croatia,</hi> whilſt theſe tranſactions were on foot, having drawn together 13000 men for the defence of that Countrey; having notice that a bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of <hi>Tartars</hi> and <hi>Turks,</hi> the Refuſe of the Garriſonupon the Frontiers, were rov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing abroad, and had done great miſchief in firing Villages, burning the Hay and Corn, raviſhing the Women, putting the men to the Sword that were unable for ſervice, and drowning the Children in the Rivers: to put a ſtop to this barbarous torrent, and to repay the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>humane Rake-Hells in their own coin, he drew out 1700 Horſe and 5000 Foot, with which croſſing the Country the neareſt way, he on the 9 of <hi>Auguſt</hi> found them triumphing in all manner of rapine
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:35052:65"/>and cruelty, when leaving 3000 Foot, and 1000 Horſe under the covert of a woody Grove, he advanced with the reſt towards the enemy; who being 6 or 7000 ſtrong, after ſome conſultation, threw themſelves into a poſture of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, and prepared to give him Battle, with whom he as reſolutely joyned, having firſt wheeled about, and taken the advantage of the Ground, ſo that he might train them into the Ambuſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and by that means incloſe them; which fell out ſo to his expectation, that after a furious charge, the Ambuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cade burſt out at their back with loud ſhouts, which they ſeconded with ſo many meſſengers of death; the enemies being as it were taken in a toil, were killed on all ſides, without making further reſiſtance, all the Plain being ſtrewed with their ruins and miſerable ſlaughter, of which not above 2000 eſcaped, the reſt being killed and taken Priſoners: Of the <hi>Croats</hi> in the firſt charge, 30 were killed, and as many wounded, and in all they loſt but 120. By this action 700 Chriſtians were deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered from miſerable captivity, and 1000
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:35052:65"/>head of Cattle recovered, with much Baggage, and ſtore of Proiviſion, which they had gathered up in the Countries through which they had paſſed; and certain it is, had not a timely ſtop been put to this torrent, before it had ſwelled great, as it would ſoon have done by the conjunction of 8000 more of the ſame Tribe, who were advancing; but upon notice of evil ſucceſs, retired: It would have put he whole Country into a great conſternation and confuſion.</p>
            <p>Count <hi>Leſlie</hi> being ſent to ſecure <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ravia</hi> from the incurſions of the enemy, with a Body of 4 or 5000 men, took a Convoy of 78 Waggons loaden with Ammunition and Proviſion, on its way to <hi>Teckely</hi>'s Camp on the banks of the <hi>Waag,</hi> putting thoſe that kept it, to flight, though without any more ſlaughter than of one man; for the Convoyers being aware of his coming, left the Waggons, and ſhifted for themſelves in the Woods. To know the ſtate of the beſieged, the Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> on the 8 of <hi>Auguſt</hi> ſent an Ingineer diſguiſed in Country habit, who under the favour of the Night paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the Leaguers, and the next night
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:35052:66"/>had the good ſucceſs to return in ſafety to the Imperial Camp; bringing an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, That the beſieged were reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute in the defence of the City, full of courage and vigor, not having loſt above 3000 men ſince the ſiege began; and that on the other hand, the <hi>Turks</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared leſs vigorous in their attempts than at firſt they did, and that they were in a manner diſtreſſed for want of Proviſion; a mortal ſickneſs at the ſame time raging in the Camp, of which ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny dyed, they not being computed to have loſt leſs than 20000 men in the divers attacks they have made in the ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies made by the beſieged, and thoſe that have periſhed by the Peſtilence, beſides ſeveral Boats full of ſick and wounded men, that have been ſent up the <hi>Danube;</hi> whilſt all the Troops of the Circles are on their march, and daily arrive at the Imperial Camp, ſo that the Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> is 38000 ſtrong, and will be 59000 ſtrong, when the <hi>Brandenburg</hi> and <hi>Bavarian</hi> Troops have joyned him, who are daily expected; ſo that in conjun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction with the King of <hi>Poland,</hi> the Army will conſiſt of 88 or 90000 fighting men,
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:35052:66"/>ſo that a mortal battle muſt of neceſſity inſue, if the Viſier raiſe not his Siege before the latter end of this Month of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> 1683.</p>
            <p>The Rebells having intelligence of the Duke of <hi>Lorrains</hi> being retired from the Walls of <hi>Presburg,</hi> with a body of 3000 Horſe and Foot, fell into <hi>Moravia,</hi> of which the Duke had no ſooner notice, but he commanded out a party of <hi>Polo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian</hi> Horſe to ſtay their advancing fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther into that fruitful Country, which party had the ſucceſs they deſired; for overtaking the Rebells as they were ravaging and plundering the Countrey, and a little before ſtrengthened, by joyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a party before in thoſe parts, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the command of the Prince of <hi>Lich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſteyne,</hi> they charged them with ſuch fury, that although they were inferior to them in number, they killed 5 or 600 upon the place, and took a like number Priſoners: Upon notice of which the Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> drew nearer to <hi>Vienna,</hi> incamping with the groſs of his Army at <hi>Enzesdorf,</hi> not far from <hi>Fienna,</hi> to be ready to ſuccour the beſieged, if oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion require it. To whom daily re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſorted
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:35052:67"/>the Troops of the Princes in mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as the Electors of <hi>Bavaria, Bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denburg, Saxony;</hi> the Princes of <hi>Newburg, Hanault,</hi> and other Territories depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant on the Empire, coming different ways for their better convenience, bringing with them great ſtore of Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion: Which obliged the <hi>Turks</hi> to preſs on the ſiege, battering the Town with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out intermiſſion, and ſpringing divers Mines, the Baſſa not ſparing the lives of his Men, but thruſt them as it were into the mouth of Slaughter, ſo that after the ſpringing the Mines, which ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ined a part of the beſiegeds Out-works, they lodged upon the Counterſcarp, and poſſeſſed it for the ſpace of an Hour; when the beſieged ſallying, beat them out with great ſlaughter, inſomuch that the Bodyes of the ſlain did not a little annoy the Imperialiſts, who uſed great diligence to countermine the <hi>Turks;</hi> which they did ſo ſuccesfully, that they met them in one of their Mines, and not only fruſtrated their deſign, but drove them out with great ſlaughter, ſeiſing on the Powder they had brought to overthrow the Palizadoes, ſo that
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:35052:67"/>maugre the <hi>Ottoman</hi> ſtratagems, they prevailed little or nothing. For the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieged incouraged by the Count <hi>d' Starem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berg</hi> their Governour, fought like Lyons, even in the Works and Breaches, made by the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Cannon, where the Shot falls thickeſt; when to encourage the Souldiers the more, the Townſmen bring out their Stores of Proviſion. Yet the <hi>Turks</hi> continuing their Mines, lodg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed themſelves under the advantage of a fifth or ſixth Mine, ſprung in the Ditch; but were ſoon ſent thence with a ſhowre of Shot ſhot from the Wall: Whereupon the Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> ſent a man into the City, to know the ſtate thereof, who by a certain ſign given, aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the Duke, that he was got ſafe into it, which ſignal was by hanging out a long blue Streamer upon the <hi>White-Tower</hi> of that City; he alſo received orders, to injoyn the Governour, if he perceived the <hi>Turks</hi> to advance ſo far, as to indan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger the place, he ſhould hang out divers Flags, as ſignals of the danger, and that rather than it ſhould fall into the hands of the Enemy, he would attempt to raiſe the ſiege without any further delay;
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:35052:68"/>but the beſieged, though they loſt a great many reſolute Souldiers, and ſome Commanders of note, declined to hang out any ſuch ſignal of danger, but brave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly defended their Works, though the <hi>Turks</hi> made frequent Aſſaults, as not expecting long to continue the ſiege, whether it came to a Battle or not, by reaſon of the great ſcarcity in their Camp: which was occaſioned by the Imperialiſts taking divers Convoys of Proviſion, inſomuch that they fed upon Horſe-fleſh as dainty fare, and an Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munition bread ſold at five Dollars; all their Forrage for their Horſes being ſo little, that 300 were ſtarved to death in one Week. Yet the Baſſa ſent again to ſummon the City, making larger offers than formerly, with many pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes of Liberty, free exerciſe of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and other immunities; which were rejected with diſdain: Whereupon he commanded a general aſſault to be made, which on the 5 and 6 of <hi>Auguſt</hi> was continued, almoſt without intermiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, thinking ſo to tire out the beſieg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and by that means oblige them to a ſurrender; but ſo far were they from
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:35052:68"/>acquiring what they aimed at, that after they had poſſeſſed themſelves of one point of the Counterſcarp, the beſieged ſprung a mine before the Work, blow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing about 100 of the Infidels into the Air, and following the advantage, ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lied at two or three Ports, upon which a ſharp conflict began, coming at length to handy-blows, in which it was not ſuppoſed, that leſs than 2000 of the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiegers fell, though at the ſame time they played againſt the wall from 7 Batteries.</p>
            <p>The City making a brave defence, a party of Imperial Horſe paſſing the <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nube,</hi> fell upon 300 <hi>Turks,</hi> who had po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted themſelves in a ſmall Iſland of what River, and put moſt of them to the Sword, bringing away 200 Camels la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den with proviſion, as alſo a great deal of rich Furniture: Of which ſucceſs the Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> had no ſooner received advice, but another Meſſenger brought him a Letter from the King of <hi>Poland</hi> to give his Highneſs an account, that he with his Army, conſiſting of between 30 and 40000 men, would be within ſight of <hi>Vienna</hi> by the 20 of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> and that he marched in three bodies for the
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:35052:69"/>better conveniency and ſpeed, deſiring the Duke not to hazzard any thing till his arrival; upon notice of which, the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour nominated the Count <hi>Schafgates</hi> to go and complement that King at his arrival on the Frontiers. Price <hi>Lubo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirski</hi> being the mean while abroad, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countered a party of the <hi>Hungarian</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels, as they were plundering on the Borders of <hi>Sileſia,</hi> and put them to the rout, killing 300 of them upon the place, and took 31 Priſoners, and 8 Enſigns, with the loſs of eight of his men, and ten wounded. Yet had not the Pala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine of <hi>Hungary</hi> the like ſucceſs, for du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring his march towards <hi>Croatia,</hi> to joyn the Viceroy, moſt of his Souldiers be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Hungarians,</hi> deſerted him by night, the greater part of them joyning with the Rebells.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Turks</hi> being earneſt to ſubdue <hi>Vienna</hi> before the arrival of the <hi>Poles,</hi> on the 16 of <hi>Auguſt</hi> made a terrible aſſault, which they continued for the ſpace of eight hours, ſpringing ſeveral Mines, by which means they became maſters of a Ravelin, and lodged themſelves upon the Counterſcarp; which cauſed the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieged
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:35052:69"/>to make a brisk ſally, and come to dint of Sword, ſo that a bloody and doubtful fight inſued: at what time the Chriſtians being reinforced, the <hi>Turks</hi> were beaten out of the Works they had taken, with the loſs of 5000 men, beſides thoſe that were wounded: Nor was the loſs inconſiderable on the part of the Imperialiſts, for in this action they loſt 150 reſolute Souldiers, and had near as many wounded; amongſt the which, were Count <hi>Staremberg</hi> and the General <hi>Souches,</hi> who adventuring too far in purſuit of the enemy, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived ſlight hurts, one being ſhot into the Legg with a <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Arrow, and the other by the ſpringing a Mine.</p>
            <p>This aſſault over, News was brought to the Imperial Camp, that Count <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prara</hi> was upon his way to the Imperial Court, and in his company a <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Aga, who had in charge to treat about raiſing the Siege of <hi>Vienna,</hi> which the Grand Signior was content to do in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration that <hi>Commorra</hi> and <hi>Raab</hi> might be put into his hands, but theſe demands ſeemed ſo unreaſonable and extravagant, that they took not effect.</p>
            <pb n="124" facs="tcp:35052:70"/>
            <p>And thus Reader have I give you an account of the ſtate of this War, ſo dangerous to Chriſtendom, from its firſt breaking out, to this day, <hi>viz.</hi> the 16 of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> 1683. according to the beſt and moſt credible advice that could be procured, and to Heaven remit the ſucceſs of the great event of the acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on at hand; the which may it happen proſperous to the Chriſtians ought to by the Prayer of every good Chriſtian: And ſo I ſhall proceed to give you a taſt of <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Cruelties uſed towards their Slaves, and ſuch as they be force or fraud carry into miſerable bondage.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="125" facs="tcp:35052:70"/>
            <head>A brief relation of the <hi>Turkiſh Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elties</hi> towards ſuch Chriſtians as they take Captives, with their man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of felling and diſpoſing them, the Labours they put them to, and their ſeveral Orders; together with the beſtiality uſed upon youths, Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>male Children and Women, by the <hi>Turks;</hi> moſt lamentable and deteſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to be told or thought.</head>
            <p>REader, having given you an account of the ſtate of the War between the two Empires of <hi>Germany</hi> and <hi>Turky,</hi> I ſhall now proceed to a more particular relation of the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> cruelties towards ſuch Ill-ſtared Chriſtians, as have the misfortune to fall into their hands, whoſe barbarity is ſuch, that they know not how to ſhew mercy, nor have compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion upon poor ſuffering wretches, who continually groan under thrice worſe than <hi>Aegyptian</hi> bondage, having none
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:35052:71"/>on Earth to appeal to for mitigation of their miſeries; yet ſuch is the courage of moſt of them, that they will rather chuſe to undergo their almoſt inſupport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able yoke under the tyranny of cruel Task-maſters, than by baſe and unchriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an cowardice deny the Lord, that bought them at the price of his precious blood, all their hopes upon earth being the expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctation of the Chriſtian Sword, under the leading of the Chriſtian Princes. But to the purpoſe.</p>
            <p>When at any time the Grand Signior has raiſed an Army for the invaſion of any Chriſtian Country, then like ſo many Vulturs or beaſts of prey, a ſort of Merchants, called by the <hi>Turks,</hi> Men-Scorcers, hover about it in great num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, to buy ſuch Captives of the rude Souldiers as they ſhall take, either in War or by ſurprize; and for that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe bring upon Camels, Mules, Drome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daries, all manner of Proviſion, Cloaths and other Merchandiſe to truck, as like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe great bundles of Cords, and Cheſts full of Chains, to tye or bind them to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, in one of which they faſten about 50 or 60 together. Theſe ſort of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:35052:71"/>Brokers, purchaſe of the Souldiers or Free-Booters, all the Captives that eſcape the Sword, with a <hi>proviſo,</hi> That the tenth fall to the ſhare of the Grand-Signior, or to the value, for they have liberty to purchaſe his Priſoners of the Tefftardar or chief Treaſurer, or his De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puties; nor have they any Merchandize ſo profitable or ſuch ſure money as Slaves, whom they hale along like dogs, or drive before them like flocks of Sheep, for the moſt part naked, expoſed to heat, cold and hunger: when if at any time they faint or are not able to go, they lay them croſs a Horſe, Mule, Camel or Dromedary, upon their Bellies, ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their Hands and Legs under the Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of the Beaſt, as they uſe in <hi>England</hi> to carry Calves; but if they find them ſick and not likely to recover, they caſt them into the next ditch, and leave them to be devoured of Wolves and other voracious Beaſts. Thoſe that are aged, being accounted unprofitable, ſeldom eſcape the Sword, unleſs they are of ſuch Eminency, that they expect a great ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome for his reſtauration: And theſe mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable Chriſtians they ſend all over the
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:35052:72"/>Empire, driving them from Market to Market like beaſts, ſo that ſometimes they carry 2 or 300 in a drove, bound in ſeveral parcels, feeding them for the moſt part with Bread and Water, or Rice Cakes.</p>
            <p>When they are newly captivated or bought, the firſt thing the Devil prompts their Patron or Maſters to, is by ſharp threats, mixed with fair promiſes to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce them to renounce their Chriſtiani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and perſwade them to admit of Circumciſion; the which if they yield to, they find ſomewhat more civil treatment, but are for ever debared of returning to their own Country, or gaining their liberty: all hope, which is ſometimes a comfort to the miſerable, is taken away till death ſet them free; and if, after they become <hi>Turks,</hi> they endeavour to eſcape, or return to the profeſſion of the Chriſtian Religion, the Law is, That they ſhall be thruſt into a hot Furnace. Such as are thought firm, and not ſubject to fly or deſert their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trons, are admitted to their Maſters mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary imployments, and can only be made free when age renders them uſeleſs, and
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:35052:72"/>that upon courteſie, for their extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary ſervice in their Youth, or ſome notable exploit, or when the Maſter up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on being hurt in the war, or in great danger of death, bequeaths him liberty. They permit them to marry, but it is to make their poſterity as well as them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves miſerable: for their Children, when they come to maturity, are made ſlave as well as themſelves; therefore thoſe that conſider the fatal conſequences that attend ſuch Matrimony, decline it. Thoſe that refuſe to be circumciſed, or to renounce their Faith in Chriſt, are miſerable, unleſs skilled in ſome extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary art, whereby they can greatly profit their Maſters. Learned Men, Prieſts, and Gentlemen, not inured to hardſhip, or capable of any Mechanick art, are miſerably dealt with; and the worſe, that they by making known their miſerable condition, by Letter, to their Friends in Chriſtendom, if they have any, may thereby be moved to ranſome them: They cauſe them to walk with naked Legs, Feet, Head, and Backs, feeding them with the bread of affliction; no new Cloaths ever ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:35052:73"/>their old ones, unleſs a little courſe Linnen to hide their Privities. And in this miſerable condition they hurry them over Rocks and Mountains, though never ſo rough and irkſome to their gall'd bleeding Feet; ſo that many times one or other dyes for loſs of blood iſſuing from his Feet, cut by Flints or ſharp Marble, and ſo ends his wretched Life: Thoſe that faulter or lag, they whip along with Scourges; and if they cannot, then they faſten them on horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>back as aforeſaid, and often torture them to make them confeſs what craft or han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy labour they are skilled in. Upon buying theſe miſerable wretches, they always feel their Joynts, to obſerve if they are ſtrong ſet, well knit, and free from imperfection; they feel likewiſe their Hands, by the hardneſs or ſoftneſs of which, they know whether they have been inured to labour or not; they have alſo eſpecial regard to their Mouth, to obſerve if they Teeth be ſtrong, firm ſet, and ſound, that ſo they be capable of eating Rice, Bisket, or any other courſe and hard Diet: And laſtly, they take great notice of their Eyes, to ſee if
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:35052:73"/>there be no dulneſs nor blemiſh in them tending to blindneſs. From theſe obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations, much the ſame as we uſe in buying Cattle, they conclude the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs or badneſs of Captives. As for their Lodging, it is in an Out-ſhed, upon stalks, Leaves of trees, or courſe Mats, not being permitted to come with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in doors, unleſs upon extraordinary occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, let the weather be never ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tream cold. As for the Women they are continually expoſed to the horrid luſts of their Merchants or Buyers, locked up in ſtrong places, and kept at hard labour, where you may hear con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinual howlings and wailings: Nor does the age of ſix years protect female chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren from the horrid luſt of theſe Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dels, nor the youths eſcape their filthy Sodomy, to which they are almoſt all of them addicted.</p>
            <p>Theſe poor wretches, <hi>viz.</hi> the men, ſome are yoked like Oxen, and forced to draw the plough, others keep Sheep upon the bleak Mountains, and ſome again till the Ground with Spades, dig up Trees, ſaw Timber, grind in Mills, waſh Cloth, fetch Water, drain Fiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponds,
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:35052:74"/>make Bricks, or the like ſervile Labours, to which they are hurried by day-light, and till night, continue at it without Meat or Drink, ſeldom being allowed any unleſs at night, unleſs they have ſome way to get money to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe it.</p>
            <p>Maids are ſeverally forced to perpetual labour, excluded both from the compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny and ſight of Men, unleſs at ſuch times as they attend their Miſtreſſes to their Country Houſes, to the Bath, or the Graves of their departed Friends.</p>
            <p>If any Man be taken Priſoner, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with his Wife and Children, he is commonly diſpoſed of to ſome Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man <hi>Turk,</hi> to be imployed in his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try houſe, there to labour in his Vineyard, till his Meadows, and plant Trees, look after his Cattle, and the like: all their Children being likewiſe made ſlaves; but if they perſevere in the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Faith, there is a time allotted fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently for their delivery; but that is always in the choice of the Maſter, and at his courteſie.</p>
            <p>If after their making free, they are deſirous to return into their own Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey,
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:35052:74"/>they have Letter Patents given them for their Journey; but this is only to ſuch as perſevere in Chriſtianity, for thoſe that abjure it, are never ſuffered to return, though ſome do now and then, by making eſcape; yet ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times they are made free, but in lieu thereof pay a certain annual ſtipend to their Maſter, and the tenth of all they poſſeſs to the Grand Signior. But moſt miſerable of all are thoſe that are ſold to Husbandmen, who for the moſt part make them draw the Plough or keep Sheep as aforeſaid; thoſe that are made Shepherds, ſeldom throughout the year come into any Houſe, but wander from Mountain to Mountain according as they can find Paſture; yet have the Maſter and Dame a Tent and a Curtain, one to lye and reſide in, the other to carry all their Furniture and Proviſion: As for the Prieſts and Clergymen, they do not only lay heavy tasks upon them, but expoſe them to all ignominy and ſcorn poſſibly, yet greatly rejoyce when by perſwaſion or compulſion, they can oblige any one of them to renounce their faith.</p>
            <pb n="134" facs="tcp:35052:75"/>
            <p>Some Turks have more humanity, and abate ſomething of this rigorous uſage, giving their Slaves now and then a ſmall Stipend, which they moſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly keep to defray their charges into Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendom, if ever they obtain their liberty; yet in this donation they have politick ends, which are to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lige them not to run away, or to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce them to imbrace the <hi>Mahumetan</hi> ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition. For ſeldom it is that they give any thing to ſuch as are already turned <hi>Mahumetans,</hi> knowing that at the peril of their lives, they attempt their flight. Their beating is unmerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, inſomuch that ſome of them lye by it 6 or 7 Weeks, and many there are that never recover, which the <hi>Turk</hi> no otherways regardeth than for his profit: for could he make as much of a Chriſtian dead as alive, they would ſuffer few or none within their power to live. Thus is the uſage of the Slaves that fall into the hands of common <hi>Turks:</hi> And now I ſhall, Reader, give you an account of the treatments of ſuch as fall to the Grand Signior by decimation, and are reſerved for his uſe,</p>
            <pb n="135" facs="tcp:35052:75"/>
            <p>The old in years, he ſells for Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band men, to be ſure if any ſuch hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen amongſt his ſhare of Priſoners, but rarely do they; for for the moſt part, the Sword devours them; theſe yield him but a ſmall and inconſiderable price, yet will they not permit them to be ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomed for thrice the value they yield. The young Men and Maids, they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fine in the <hi>Seraglios,</hi> there to be taught and inſtructed in uſeful Arts, as making Bows, Arrows, Carpets, and the like; but firſt they oblige them to a renuntiati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of their Faith, and to be Circumciſed, diligently obſerving their Lineaments, Features, and the like; as alſo their prompt Wit and aptneſs, and accordingly they bring them up, ſome to Artifices, others to learn the <hi>Mahumetan</hi> Law, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers to exerciſe Arms, and allow them a ſtipend of two or three Aſpers a day, to provide them with Cloaths and Diet, till they are perfected, 60 of which Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers make a Crown <hi>Engliſh.</hi> Over them they have ſevere Task-maſters, to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act a daily account of their Exerciſe; and if they perform it not, then are they unmercifully beaten with Rods, Staves,
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:35052:76"/>or other things of more cruel invention. When they begin to grow perfect, they are inrolled, ſome in the order of the Bowmen, other ſome in the order of the Janizaries, and thoſe that have lovely Faces are expoſed to the horrid and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domitical luſt of their abominable lords; and for that purpoſe the Genitals are cut away: ſo that when they have been uſed as long as the <hi>Turk</hi> things convenient, then are they put to the offices of Eunuchs, to attend on the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy-Concubines Horſes, Mules, or ſome Kitchen imploy.</p>
            <p>Virgins, ſuch as are of extraordinary beauty, comelineſs or compoſition of Body, are choſen out for Concubines, and thruſt into a more narrow retire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Thoſe that are but indifferent handſome, they put to attend upon others, and to waſh the privy parts of the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Women after they have eva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuated, which is a thing always obſerved amongſt them. Others they imploy at ſpinning, winding Silk, weaving Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pets, carding Wooll, and the like, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving firſt obliged them to renounce the Chriſtian Faith; for no Chriſtian may
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:35052:76"/>be ſuffered to inhabit within the Wall of the <hi>Seraglio;</hi> and from theſe are cut off all hopes of returning into their own Countrey, being obliged in a ſtrong and barbarous Land, to bewail their hard fates and wretched Captivity, wiſhing that they had fallen by the Sword amongſt their Friends, rather than to be excluded from all humane ſociety, unleſs ſuch as is more deteſtable and hateful to them than <hi>Cimmerian</hi> dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs it ſelf, which frequently drives them into ſuch deſpair, that they lay vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olent hands upon themſelves, chuſing ſtrangling rather than life, others pine away, and ſome ſtarve themſelves to death on purpoſe, others are beaten till of the blows and bruiſes they expire, and thus miſerable wretches is their ſtate un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the triumphing tyranny of the barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Infidels, who know not how to ſhew mercy.</p>
            <p>The manner of making Chriſtians <hi>Turks,</hi> and to renounce their Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Religion is thus: The Mufti, or Chief Prieſt, or ſome of his Agents, after the Circumciſion, which is done by cutting off their Foreskin with a
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:35052:77"/>ſharp Knife, obliges them to ſay theſe words in the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Language after them, <hi>viz. Law illawheh illaw Allawh Muhammed reſoul Allawh:</hi> that rendred into <hi>Engliſh</hi> is thus, <hi>There is no God but one alone, and Mahumet is his Meſſenger or Prophet.</hi> The Women and Virgins on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſay the words, as not being capable of the former part of the Ceremony. Another way the Grand Signior has to get Slaves than by War, <hi>viz.</hi> All the Chriſtian Provinces, his tributaries, or ſuch Chriſtians as live in his dominions, pay tribute-Children, having their Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren ſnatched from them at the age of three or four years, and theſe are taught the <hi>Mahumetan</hi> Superſtition, and put under the tutorage of divers ſevere Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, to be inſtructed and educated in all manner of Arts, but eſpecially in feats of Arms, and out of theſe they chuſe the Janizaries and Spahi, which are for Horſe and Foot, the ſupport of the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Empire, being more dead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly enemies to the Chriſtians than natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral born <hi>Turks.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="139" facs="tcp:35052:77"/>
            <p>From theſe and the like miſeries poor wretches divers times attempt making their eſcape, which they cannot do without great danger and hazzard of their lives, eſpecially ſuch as are in <hi>Aſia,</hi> for they have no way to get into <hi>Europe,</hi> but by ſwimming over the <hi>Helleſpont</hi> into <hi>Europe.</hi> which cannot be effected with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out great danger, and frequent loſs of Lives. But becauſe many may imagine that in ſo large a dominion, theſe poor wretches may eaſily ſhift from their cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el Maſters, eſpecially ſuch as are imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed abroad, I ſhall to convince that, ſpeak ſomething of that matter, and ſo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed to give a more particular account of the preſent miſeries of <hi>Hungary</hi> and <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtria,</hi> than in the ſeries of this Hiſtory has occurred.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>European</hi> Slaves indeed with more fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cility make their eſcapes than thoſe that are ſold into <hi>Aſia, Aegypt,</hi> and the Iſlands of the Sea, by reaſon they have only Rivers to paſs, which for the moſt part, at ſome place or another are fordable, or ſo narrow that they may eaſily be ſwum over; but ſuch as are in <hi>Aſia,</hi> muſt of neceſſity paſs the <hi>Helleſpont,</hi> as is afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid,
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:35052:78"/>and ſuch as deſign it, for the moſt part, attempt it in Harveſt time, by that means ſheltering themſelves in fields of Corn all day, and by night travel; Corn and Herbs being their only Food, the greateſt part of their Journey, they car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying no other Proviſion than Salt, to ſeaſon them; and in this manner their lives are expoſed to ravening Wolves, Bears and Lyons, chooſing rather to be devoured, if it ſhould happen ſo, then to return to their Curriſh Maſters, whoſe mercies are cruelty.</p>
            <p>When they come to the <hi>Helleſpont,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween <hi>Callipolis</hi> and the Towns of <hi>Seſtos</hi> and <hi>Abydos,</hi> which guard the Straight, called by the <hi>Turks, Begaz Aſſer,</hi> they cut down Timber, and make Floats or Rafts, upon which they get, ſometimes to the number of 20 or 30, carrying no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing with them but Salt and Herbs, when if the Wind prove favourable, they are waſted to the <hi>European</hi> Shoar, in five or ſix Hours, which they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude a fortunate ſign, or preſage of their eſcaping out of miſerable thraldom; but if the wind prove contrary, or the Sea rage high, they are carryed away with
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:35052:78"/>the ſtream into the main Ocean, where they inevitably periſh, unleſs ſome Ship happen in time to take them up, or ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times being forced back upon the <hi>Aſian</hi> Shore, they fall into the hands of their purſuers; but if they can attain the wiſhed Shoar, they betake themſelves to the Mountains, and by the guidance of the Stars, paſs North and North<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weſt, living upon Roots, Acorns and Herbs; unleſs now and then they can plunder a Shepherds Tent of Proviſion, in attempting of which ſome of them are frequently killed, and ſometimes they kill the <hi>Turks;</hi> but if they chance to be taken and returned to their old Maſters, then woe is them, their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition is more miſerable than before, and better it had been for them, if they had dyed ere they had been born; for then they are not only load<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with chains of Iron about their Waſtes and Necks, of an extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary weight, which bend them al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt double, and obliged to wear them during the pleaſure of their cruel Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tron, and in the mean time work and labour not only like Horſes, but
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:35052:79"/>hung up by the Heels, and ſcourged till deep furrows are made in their Backs and Sides, and in that bleed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and wretched poſture, rubbed o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver with Gunpowder, Salt-Peter or powder of Glaſs; and there ſuffered to hang in miſerable torment, till or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der is given for their taking down, which ſometimes is not the pleaſure of the imperious <hi>Turk</hi> under eight or ten Hours; ſo that in vain they wiſh for death that frees them. Others have the Soals of their Feet gaſhed or ripped, and Salt rammed into the wounds with Sticks or Irons made for that purpoſe. Some again they confine in dark and diſmal Dunge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons full of Toads, Mice, and all manner of noiſome and offenſive Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine; where they many times ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer them to periſh through Hunger, Thirſt, Cold or noyſomeneſs of the place; or ſometimes to rid them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves of a miſerable life, they raſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and unadviſedly daſh their own Brains out againſt the Walls. And thus, Reader, is the miſerable ſtate of ſuch as fall into the hands of the
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:35052:79"/>mercileſs barbarians, though in their flight they are often aſſiſted by the <hi>Greeks,</hi> who are Chriſtians, theſe men hazzarding their Lives and confiſcation of all their Goods frequently to preſerve them; for ſuch is the Law, that if any under the Grand Signiors protection ſhall be aiding or concealing, maintain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or comforting Slaves in their flight. Theſe good men, often, notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing do harbour them in their Houſes, and procure Shipping for their paſſage into <hi>Italy,</hi> or other Chriſtian Countreys; but in theſe attempts more loſe their Lives by the dangers of Travelling, Shipwrack, Enemies, wild-Beaſts, and ſtarving, than eſcape, or poſſibly can eſcape.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Turks</hi> have an incantation, which they hold effectual to prevent the flight of their Slaves, which thus they perform: The name of the Slave they write in parchment, and hang it up in the Houſe or Tent, according as they are furniſhed; for ſome of them have no Houſes, but wander after their Flocks in Tents, the which having done with horrible Curſes and Imprecations, they
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:35052:80"/>charge the Slave, if ever he attempt to eſcape, ſwearing by <hi>Mahumet,</hi> that all the curſe that can be invented will befal him, if he do; conceiving that this by the help of the Devil, will afright the fugitive, with the fear of meeting Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, Bears, Dragons, Tigers, and Wolves, in his way, that he ſhall pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh by hunger, be ſwallowed up by the Rivers, or be intombed in the depth of the Sea, or that the Heavens will grow diſmal and black, and tempeſtuous ſtorms ariſe, inſomuch that theſe aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments will bring him back, and indeed they have their wiſhed effects upon the <hi>Mahumetan</hi> Slaves: but thoſe that believe in Chriſt, and revere his name, cannot be Bug-beared with things altogether ridiculous and inſignificant; and therefore after ſuch they look more narrowly, having ſpies in divers parts to give notice of their flight, and to purſue them, between whom and the Fugitives happen ſharp incounters, inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much, that ſome on either ſide are fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently killed, the Slaves chuſing ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to dye fighting like men, than to be brought back, to be tortured and
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:35052:80"/>uſed worſe than Dogs; if thoſe that are returned have killed any perſon, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though in their own defence, then are they dipped over Head and Ears in a Cauldron of boyling Oyl; then taken out, being alive, and caſt into a deep Dungeon, and there ſuffered to periſh, or elſe have their fleſh launced, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing rubbed over with Honey, or ſome ſweet liquor, are hanged up alive for the Bees, Hornets, Waſps, and ſuch In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects to prey upon: and in that miſerable condition, frequently do the Vulturs and other rapacious Fowl feed upon and tear them, whilſt living, and in this condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſome hang 4 or 5, nay ſometimes 6 or 7 dayes, before they dye: Others they wrap up in Bears Skins, or Swines Skins, and expoſe them to the fury of Dogs, with which they bait them to Death. Theſe and many more are the Torments theſe poor Creatures indure, under their cruel Maſters,</p>
            <p>Thoſe that are taken by the <hi>Tartars</hi> are worſe uſed, if worſe can poſſible be, for they having little or no imployment, for them, (as being a roving, thieviſh, and uncivilized people, living altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:35052:81"/>upon theft and rapine, eſpecially that part adjoyning to Chriſtendom) they keep them in dark places, cruelly beating and torturing them, thereby to oblige them to ſend their lamentable ſtories to their Friends in Chriſtendom, (which indeed are ſuch as might move hearts of Flint) thereby to incite and ſtir them up to purchaſe them at great Ranſoms: for to that end do the <hi>Tartars</hi> carry them away, and if they find with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in one year, that no enquiry is made af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter them, nor any ranſome likely to be obtained, then do they fell them to the <hi>Turks;</hi> of which viciſſitude divers of them are glad, although the change is moſt miſerable, for as the old Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verb amongſt us is, <hi>They,</hi> as it were, <hi>leap out of the Frying-pan into the Fire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thus Reader, are the miſeries of poor afflicted Captives, whoſe part, during their being in ſervice, none dare take but Heaven, to whom they ſigh and cry aloud for deliverance, filling the Air with plaints, lamentations and woes ſtill groaning under the oppreſſing ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny of their cruel Task-maſters, who exceed thoſe of <hi>Aegypt,</hi> for they not
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:35052:81"/>only oblige them to make Brick with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Straw, but feed them continually with Bread of Affliction, ſtripes, and daily menaces, tempting them hourly to deny the Lord that bought them with his precious blood, thereby ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſtingly to damn their precious and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal Souls; whoſe name, they to their grief, are obliged to hear blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheemed, reproached, and his God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head reviled and contemned.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:35052:82"/>
            <head>Advertiſement.</head>
            <p>THE Hiſtory of the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> War, with the <hi>Rhodians, Venetians, Egyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians, Perſians,</hi> and other Nations: Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a compact <hi>Series</hi> of the memorable Battels, Sieges, and progreſs of the <hi>Ot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toman</hi> Armies in <hi>Europe, Aſia,</hi> and <hi>Afri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca,</hi> for near an hundred years: With their various ſucceſs by Sea and Land. But a relation more particularly of the firſt bloody Siege of <hi>Rhodes,</hi> in the reign of <hi>Mahumet</hi> the Great, Emperour of the <hi>Turks;</hi> and the laſt under the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of <hi>Solyman</hi> the Magnificent, who, at the expence of an 100000 Lives, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally ſubdued that famous City and I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſland, defended by the Valour of the Renowned <hi>Peter Aubuſſon,</hi> Grand Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of <hi>Rhodes,</hi> and the Chriſtian Knights of the Order of S. <hi>John,</hi> againſt the whole Power of the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Empire, for 230 Years. With a pathetick ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of many other remarkable paſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges; Written by <hi>Will. Caourſin,</hi> Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellor of the Order, and <hi>Rhodgia Afendy,</hi> a <hi>Turk.</hi> Printed for <hi>Will. Whitwood,</hi> next to the <hi>George Inn</hi> in <hi>Little Britain.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:35052:82"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:35052:83"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:35052:83"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
